<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Count of Gabalis, or, Conferences about secret sciences rendered out of French into English by A.L. ...</title>
            <title>Comte de Gabalis. English</title>
            <author>Villars, abbé de (Nicolas-Pierre-Henri), 1635-1673.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95921</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V386B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R226487</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475269</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475269</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151429</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95921)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151429)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2258:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Count of Gabalis, or, Conferences about secret sciences rendered out of French into English by A.L. ...</title>
                  <title>Comte de Gabalis. English</title>
                  <author>Villars, abbé de (Nicolas-Pierre-Henri), 1635-1673.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 126, [14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. James for Robert Harford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: 6 p.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rosicrucians.</term>
               <term>Occultism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151429:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE COVNT OF GABALIS: OR, CONFERENCES ABOUT Secret Sciences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Rendered out of <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> A. L. <hi>A. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Quod tanto impendio abſconditur, etian ſolummodo demonſtrare deſtruere eſt <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> Tho. James <hi>for</hi> Robert Harford, <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in</hi> Cornhil, <hi>near the</hi> Royal Exchange,</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151429:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151429:2"/>
            <head>The Count of GABALIS: OR, Conferenccs about Secret Sciences.</head>
            <div n="1" type="conference">
               <head>The Firſt Conference about Secret Sciences.</head>
               <p>PEACE be with the Soul of the Noble Count of <hi>GABALIS,</hi> who, as I am informed by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, died lately of an <hi>Apoplexy.</hi> The curious Heads, I know, will be ſure to ſay that that is a common Death to thoſe who are bad husbands of the Secrets of the <hi>Sages;</hi> and that ever ſince the bleſſed <hi>Raymond Lully</hi> pronounced the Sentence in his laſt will, his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151429:3"/> an Angel is always ready to wring off the Neck of all thoſe who indiſcreetly reveal the Myſteries of Philoſophers.</p>
               <p>But let them not be raſh in condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Learned Man, without being clearly informed of his Conduct; It is true, he diſcovered all to me, but it was with all imaginable Cabaliſtick cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection. This is a teſtimony due to the memory of him who was zealous in the Religion of his Fathers the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, and who would have burnt, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than prophaned its Sanctity, by opening his mind to any undeſerving <hi>Prince,</hi> to any ambitious or inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>Perſon;</hi> three ſorts of People in all times excommunicated by the <hi>Sages.</hi> I have the good fortune not to be a <hi>Prince,</hi> I have but little <hi>Ambition,</hi> and it will appear in the ſequel that I have even a little more <hi>Chaſtity</hi> than is requiſite to a <hi>Philoſopher:</hi> He found me of a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile mind, curious, and not eaſie ſtartled I want but a little <hi>Melancholy</hi> to make all thoſe who blame the Count of <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> for having concealed nothing from me, acknowledge that I was a Suject proper enough for <hi>Secret Sciences.</hi> The
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151429:3"/> truth is, without <hi>Melancholy</hi> no great progreſs can be made in them; but the little that I had, did not diſcourage him. You have (he has many times told me) <hi>Saturn</hi> in an Angle, in his Houſe and retrograde; you cannot but one day be as <hi>Melancholy</hi> as a <hi>Sage</hi> ought to be; for the wiſeſt of Men (as we know in the <hi>Cab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l</hi>) had, as you have, <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cendant, and yet it is not known that ever he laughed in his life time; ſo powerful was the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his <hi>Saturn,</hi> though it was much weaker than yours.</p>
               <p>It is my <hi>Saturn</hi> then, and not the Count of <hi>Gabalis,</hi> that the curious Heads ſhould quarrel with, if I like better to divulge than practice their <hi>Secrets.</hi> If the <hi>Stars</hi> fail in their duty, the Count of <hi>Gabalis</hi> is not in the fault; and if I have not that greatneſs of <hi>Soul,</hi> as to aſpire to become Maſter of <hi>Nature,</hi> to overturn the Elements, to converſe with ſupream <hi>Intelligences,</hi> to command <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rits,</hi> to create <hi>New Worlds,</hi> to ſpeak to <hi>God</hi> in his dreadful <hi>Throne,</hi> and to oblige the <hi>Cherubin</hi> that guards the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the <hi>Earthly Paradiſe,</hi> to let me
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151429:4"/> fetch ſome walks in the <hi>Garden;</hi> I am the onely <hi>Perſon</hi> that am moſt to be blamed: <hi>Men</hi> muſt not therefore inſult over the memory of that rare <hi>Man,</hi> and ſay that he died, becauſe he told me ſo many things. Is it impoſſible, but that he may have fallen in a Combat with ſome rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Goblin,</hi> ſeing the fortune of <hi>War</hi> is various? Perhaps talking to God in his inflamed <hi>Throne,</hi> he could not forbear to look in his <hi>Face:</hi> Now it is written, <hi>That no Man can ſee his Face and live.</hi> It may be he is only dead in appearance, according to the cuſtom of <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> who ſeem to die in one place and tranſport themſelves to another. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the matter be, I cannot believe that the manner how he intruſted me with his <hi>Treaſures,</hi> deſerves any puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And now I'll tell ye how it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened:</p>
               <p>Common ſenſe having made me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſuſpect that there was a great deal of emptineſs in what they call, <hi>Secret Science,</hi> I was never tempted to caſt away my time in turning over the Books that treat on them; but likewiſe thinking it unreaſonable, without any ground, to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151429:4"/> condemn all others that apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to that <hi>Study,</hi> who are otherways many times Diſcreet and Learned Men, and in repute both for the Gown and Sword; I thought it my beſt (that I might not be unjuſt, nor cumbered with tedious <hi>Study</hi>) to pretend my ſelf ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with all thoſe <hi>Sciences,</hi> when I met with any that I could learn were touched with the ſame. I had at firſt better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs than I could even have expected. For how myſteriouſly reſerved ſoever theſe Blades affect to be, yet they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire no better than to vent their imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and the new diſcoveries that they pretend to have made in <hi>Nature;</hi> ſo that in a few days I became the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of the chiefeſt of them: I never wanted one or other of them in my <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> which I had purpoſely furniſhed with their fantaſtical <hi>Authors.</hi> No Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Stranger paſſed this way but I had notice of it; and in a word, in a very ſhort time I wanted nothing, if ye'll ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the <hi>Sciences,</hi> to make me a great <hi>Perſon, Princes,</hi> great <hi>Lords, Gown-men,</hi> fair <hi>Ladies,</hi> and ugly ones too, <hi>Doctors, Prelates, Monks, Nuns,</hi> and all ſorts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151429:5"/> of <hi>People</hi> were my <hi>Companions.</hi> Some were for <hi>Angels,</hi> ſome for the <hi>Devil;</hi> ſome for their <hi>Genius,</hi> ſome for <hi>Incubus</hi>'s; ſome for the cure of all <hi>Diſeaſes,</hi> ſome for the <hi>Stars,</hi> ſome for the <hi>Secrets</hi> of <hi>Divinity,</hi> and generally all for the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers Stone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They all agreed that thoſe great <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets,</hi> and eſpecially the <hi>Philoſophers Stone,</hi> are hard to be found out, and that few poſſeſs them; but every one of them had ſo good an opinion of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in particular, as to believe they were of the number of the Elect. By good fortune at that time the chief of the Tribe impatiently expected the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a <hi>German Lord</hi> and great <hi>Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt,</hi> whoſe Lands lie towards the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of <hi>Poland:</hi> He promiſed, by Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to come and viſit the Children of the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> and to paſs from <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> I was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to write an Anſwer to the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of that great Man, and therewith ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im the figure of my <hi>Nativity,</hi> that he might judge by it if I might aſpire to ſupream <hi>Wiſdom.</hi> My <hi>Figure</hi> and <hi>Letter</hi> had the good fortune to procure the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151429:5"/> honour of this Anſwer from him, <hi>That I ſhould be one of the firſt he would ſee at</hi> Paris, <hi>and that if Heaven oppoſed not, it ſhould not be his fault if I were not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the ſociety of the</hi> Sages.</p>
               <p>That I might improve this happineſs, I kept a regular correſpondence with this illuſtrious <hi>German.</hi> Now and then I propoſed to him great <hi>Doubts,</hi> backed with as much <hi>Reaſon</hi> as I could, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Harmony of the <hi>World,</hi> the Numbers of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> the Revelation of St. <hi>John,</hi> and the firſt Chapter of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis.</hi> The ſumblimity of theſe matters raviſhed him, he wrote to me of ſtrange and unheard of <hi>Wonders;</hi> and I well perceived that I had to do with a Man of a ſtrong and vaſt <hi>Imagination</hi> I have about Three or four ſcore of his Letters, of ſo extraordinary a ſtile, that whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I was alone in my Study, I could read nothing but them.</p>
               <p>One day as I was admiring one of the ſublimeſt of them, a Man of an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent meene entered my Study, who ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting me with Gravity, ſaid to me in <hi>French,</hi> but with the accent of a ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: <hi>Adore, my Son, ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re the great and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151429:6"/> good God of the</hi> Sages, <hi>and let it never puff you up with Pride, that he ſends one of the Children of Wiſdom, to receive you into their Society, and to impart to you the Wonders of his Omnipotence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I was a little aſtoniſhed at the novelty of the <hi>Greeting,</hi> and began at firſt to doubt whether Men have not Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſometimes: however re-aſſuring my ſelf as well as I could, and looking on him with as much Civility as the little fear that I was in could allow of; <hi>Whoever you be,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>you whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment is not of this World, you do me much honour by this Viſit; but do me the favour, if you pleaſe, that before I adore the God of the</hi> Sages, <hi>I may know what</hi> Sages <hi>you mean, and of what God you ſpeak; if it be with your conveniency, take that Seat, and tell me what</hi> God, Sages, Secrecy, <hi>and</hi> Wonders <hi>of</hi> Omnipotence, <hi>are thoſe you talk of; and firſt or laſt, as you pleaſe, to what ſort of Creature I have the honour to ſpeak.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You receive me Sir very wiſely</hi> (anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he laughing, and taking the Seat I offered him) <hi>You deſire me at firſt to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part matters to you, which if you pleaſe,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151429:6"/> I ſhall not do too day. The Compliment I made you, are the words of the</hi> Sages, <hi>when firſt they accoſt thoſe whom they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to open their heart unto, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their Myſteries. I thought that being ſo Learned, as you have appeared to me by your Letters, that Salutation would not have ſurprized you; and that it ſhould have been the moſt acceptable Compliment that the Count of</hi> Gabalis <hi>could make you. Ah! Sir,</hi> cried I (calling to mind the great part I had to act) <hi>How ſhall I do to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve ſo much goodneſs? Is it poſſible that the greateſt of Men is now in my Study, and that the great Count of</hi> Gabalis <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours me with a Viſit?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am the leaſt of</hi> Sages (replied he with a ſerious Countenance) <hi>and God who diſpenſes the Rays of his wiſdom, with the weight and meaſure that beſt pleaſes his Majeſty, has beſtowed on me but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmall portion, in reſpect of that which with aſtoniſhment I admire in my Fellows. I am in hopes that you may one day equal them, if I dare judge ſo by the Figure of your Nativity, which you did me the honour to ſend me: But give me leave Sir</hi> (ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he laughing) <hi>to blame you for having
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151429:7"/> at firſt taken me for an Appartion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ah! not for an Apparition</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>but I confeſs, Sir, that calling to mind of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, how</hi> Cardan <hi>reports that his Father was viſited one day in his Study by ſeven Strangers clothed in different Colours, who diſcourſed to him very odly of their Nature and Imployment. — I underſtand you</hi> (ſaid the Count, interrupting me) <hi>they were</hi> Sylphes, <hi>of whom I ſhall one day talk to you, who are a kind of aereal Subſtance, that come ſometimes to conſult the</hi> Sages <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Books of</hi> Averroes, <hi>which they are not over-skill'd in,</hi> Cardan <hi>was a Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head for publiſhing that in his Book of</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilities; <hi>he f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>und the Memoires amongſt the Books of his Father, who was one of us, and who perceiving his Son to be naturally a blab tongue would not inſtruct him in any thing that was ſublime, but let him onely tamper and amuſe himſelf with ordinary</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrology; <hi>by which he could not ſo much as foreſee that his Son ſhould be hanged. That Rogue is the cauſe you did me the wrong to take me for a</hi> Sylphe. <hi>Wrong</hi> (replied I) <hi>How, Sir, am I then ſo unhappy as .... that does not trouble me</hi> (ſaid he, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting) <hi>you are not obliged to know that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151429:7"/> all thoſe elementary</hi> Spirits <hi>are our Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that they are too much honoured when we condeſcend to instruct them; and that the leaſt of our</hi> Sages <hi>is more knowing and powerful than all theſe dandy prat Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. But we ſhall diſcourſe of that another time; it is enough for too day that I have had the ſatisfaction to ſee yeu. Endeavonr my Son to become worthy of receiving the</hi> Cabaliſtick Light; <hi>the hour of your Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration is come; and you your ſelf muſt be in the fault if you become not a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Pray ardently to him who alone has the power of creating new Hearts, that he would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ive you one capable of the great matters that I have to tell you, and that he would put it into my heart to keep from you none of his Myſteries.</hi> With that he aroſe, and embracing me, without giving me time to anſwer, <hi>Farewel my Son</hi> (continued he) <hi>I muſt go ſee our Friends who are here at</hi> Paris, <hi>and when that is done you ſhall hear of me. In the mean time,</hi> Watch, pray, hope, and hold your peace.</p>
               <p>Having ſaid ſo, he went out of my Study; and as I waited upon him out, I complained of the ſhortneſs of his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151429:8"/> and that he had the Cruelty to leave me ſo ſoon, after he had given me a glimpſe of his extraordinary Knowledge. But having with very good Grace aſſured me that I ſhould loſe nothing by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, he took Coach, and left me in a ſurprize not to be expreſſed. I could not believe my Eyes or Ears; <hi>I am ſure</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>that this is a Man of great Quality, that he hath an Eſtate of Fifty thouſand Livers a year; and appears otherways to be a very accompliſhed Perſon: Can he be gulled with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe Follies? He has talked very gallantly to me of</hi> Sylphes. <hi>Is he in effect a Sorcerer, and have I been hitherto in a miſtake, in believing that there were none? But likewiſe, if there be Sorcerers, are they as devote as this Man ſeems to be?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I could not tell what to think of all this, yet I was reſolved to ſee what it would come to, though I well fore-ſaw that I ſhould be baited with Sermons, and that the Familiar which preſſed him was a great moraliſt and holder forth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="conference">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:151429:8"/>
               <head>The Second Conference about Secret Science.</head>
               <p>THe Count was willing to give me the whole night to ſpend in Prayer, and next morning by break of day he acquainted me by a Note that he would come to my Houſe about Eight of the Clock, and that if I thought fit we ſhould go abroad and take the Air together. He came according to his promiſe, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mutual Civilities paſt; Let us go (ſaid he) to ſome place where we may be at liberty, and where our Conference may not be interrupted. <hi>Ruel,</hi> ſaid I, ſeems to me both pleaſant and ſolitary enough. Let us go thither then, replied he, ſo we took Coach, and on the way I carefully obſerved my new Maſter. I never remarked ſo great a ſtock of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in any Man, as appeared in all his Carriage; he had a more ſedate and compoſed mind, than a Sorcerer I thought could have. He had the aſpect of a Man whoſe Conſcience upbraided
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151429:9"/> him with nothing that was foul; and I was very impatient to hear him enter upon the matter; not being able to conceive, how a Man who in all things elſe appeared to me ſo judicious and accompliſhed, could be deluded by the Viſions with which I perceived him inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted the day before. He talked Divinely of Policy, and was raviſhed to hear that I had read <hi>Plato</hi> on that Subject. You'll need all that one day (ſaid he) more than now you are aware of; and if we fadge to day, it is not impoſſible but that in proceſs of time you may have occaſion to put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice thoſe <hi>Sage<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>-Maximes. With that we entered into <hi>Ruel,</hi> and went into the Garden; but the Count diſdaining to admire the Beauties of the place, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſtraight towards the <hi>Labyrinth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Perceiving that we were in as ſolitary a place as he could deſire; I praiſe (cried he, lifting up his Eyes and Hands to Heaven) I prai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the Eternal Wiſdom, that he hath put it into my mind to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal nothing from you of his ineffable Truth. How happy will you be, my Son! if he have the goodneſs to endue your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151429:9"/> Soul with the Diſpoſitions that ſo high Myſteries require. You are now to learn how to command all Nature; God alone ſhall be your Maſter, and the <hi>Sages</hi> onely your Peers. The ſupream Intelligences ſhall think it their honour to obey your deſires; the Devils ſhall not dare to appear where you are, your voice ſhall make them tremble in the pottomleſs Pit, and all the inviſible Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who inhabit the four Elements, will reckon themſelves happy to be the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of your Pleaſures. I adore thee, O great God! in that thou haſt crowned Man with ſo much Glory, and made him Monarch over all the Works of thine Hands. Do you feel my Son (ſaid he turning to me) do you feel that Heroick Ambition, which is a ſure Character of the Children of Wiſdom? Dare you deſire to ſerve none but God alone, and to bear rule over every thing which is not God? Have you learnt yet what it is to be Man? And is it not tedious to you to be a Slave; ſeeing you are born to be Soveraign? And if you entertain thoſe noble thoughts, as the Figure of your Nativity ſuffers me not to doubt, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151429:10"/> deliberately with your ſelf if you have the Courage and Reſolution to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all things that may be a hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to you in attaining to that pitch of Elevation for which you are born? He ſtopt there, and fixed his Eyes upon me, as if he expected my Anſwer, or endeavoured to read it in my heart.</p>
               <p>How much the beginning of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe made me hope that we ſhould quickly come to the point, ſo much did his laſt words make me deſpair of it. The word <hi>Renounce</hi> ſtarttled me, and I made no doubt but that he was going to propoſe to me the renouncing of my Baptiſm or Paradiſe. So not knowing which way to come off: Renounce Sir (ſaid I) how! muſt I renounce any thing then? Without doubt you muſt (replied he) and that is ſo abſolutely neceſſary, that it is the firſt thing you muſt do. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell if you can reſolve to do it: But I know very well that Wiſdom dwells not in a body ſubject to ſin, as it enters not into a Soul prepoſſeſſed with error or malice. The <hi>Sages</hi> will never admit of you into their Society, if you renounce not one thing which is inconſiſtent with wiſdom.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151429:10"/> 
                  <hi>You muſt</hi> (added he very ſoftly, laying his Mouth to my Ear) <hi>renounce all Carnal dealing with Women.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At that odd Propoſition I burſt forth in Laughter. You have let me go upon very eaſie terms; Sir (ſaid I) I expected you ſhould have propoſed to me ſome ſtrange Renunciation; but ſince all your Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel is with Women, the thing is done long ago: I am chaſte enough, I thank God for it: Nevertheleſs Sir, ſince <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> was a wiſer Man than ever I ſhall be perhaps, and that all his Wiſdom could not hinder him from being cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: Tell me, if you pleaſe, what Expedient do ye Gentlemen of the <hi>Cabal</hi> take to forgo that Sex; and what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience would it be if in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of Philoſophers every <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould have his <hi>Eve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You ask great Matters (replied he) conſulting with himſelf if he ſhould An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer my Queſtion) Nevertheleſs ſince I perceive that you will without difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty renounce Women, I will tell you one of the Reaſons which hath obliged the <hi>Sages</hi> to exact this condition from their Diſciples; and by that you'll know
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151429:11"/> in what Ignorance live all thoſe who are not of our number.</p>
               <p>When you ſhall be liſted among the Children of the Philoſophers, and your Eyes fortified by the uſe of the moſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Medicine; you'll at firſt diſcover that the Elements are inhabited by moſt perfect Creatures, whom the ſin of wretched <hi>Adam</hi> hath deprived his too wretched Poſterity of the Knowledge of. This immenſe ſpace which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Earth and the Heavens, has far more noble Inhabitants than Birds and Gnats; thoſe vaſt Seas have many other Gueſts beſides Whales and Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phins; the depth of the Earth is not made onely for Moles; and the more noble Element of Fire was not created to remain void and uſeleſs.</p>
               <p>The Air is full of an innumerable mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of People of Humane Shape, in appearance ſomewhat fierce, but in reality tractable; great lovers of Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Subtle, Officious to the <hi>Sages,</hi> and the Enemies of the Fooliſh and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Their Wives and Daughters are Maſculine Beauties, ſuch as they paint the <hi>Amazones.</hi> How Sir (cried I) would
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151429:11"/> you make me believe that thoſe <hi>Goblins</hi> are married?</p>
               <p>Startle not, my Son, at ſo ſmall a matter (replied he) believe that what I tell you is a ſolid truth; theſe are but the Elements of the Ancient <hi>Cabal,</hi> and it ſhall be no Mans fault but your own if your own Eyes convince you not; but receive with a docile mind the Knowledge which God ſends to you by my Miniſtery. Forget all that you may have learnt of thoſe things in the Schools of the Ignorant; for it will vex you, when you are convinced by experience, to be forced to confeſs that you have been wilful out of purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Hear me out then, and know that the Seas and Rivers are inhabited as well as the Air; the Anc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent <hi>Sages</hi> named that kind of People, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndians</hi> or <hi>Nymphs.</hi> They begat few Males, and Women a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound amongſt them; they are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly Beautiful, and the Daughters of Men are not to be compared to them.</p>
               <p>The Earth is filled almoſt to the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with <hi>Gnomes,</hi> a People of a low Stature, the Guardians of Treaſures,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151429:12"/> Mines and precious Stones. They are Ingenious, Friends to Man, and eaſie to be commanded. They ſupply the Children of the <hi>Sages</hi> with what Money they need, and deſire no other Wages for their Service but the Glory of being commanded. The <hi>Gnom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>des</hi> their Wives are little, but very pretty, and very curious in their Cloths.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Salamanders,</hi> the inflamed In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Fiery Region; they ſerve Philoſophers, but are not ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to court their Company, and their Daughters and Wives ſuffer themſelves rarely to be ſeen. They have reaſon (ſaid I, interrupting him) and I excuſe them from their appearance. Why? (ſaid the Count) Why, Sir (replied I) and what have I to do to converſe with ſo ugly a Beaſt as a <hi>Salamander,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Male or Female? You are in the wrong (replied he) that is the notion that ignorant Painters and Engravers have of them: The Wives of <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> are Beautiful, and even more love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than all the reſt, ſeeing they are of a purer Element. I will not inſiſt long
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151429:12"/> in the diſcription of thoſe People, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you your ſelf ſhall ſee them eaſily and at leiſure, if you have the curioſity. You ſhall ſee their Dreſs, their Diet, their Manners, Government, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Laws. You will be more charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Beauty of their Mind, than with that of their Body; but you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but pity theſe poor wretches, when they tell you that their Soul is mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and that they have no hopes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy that Eternal Being which they know, and religiouſly adore. They'll tell you that being compoſed of the pureſt parts of the Elements which they inhabit, and having no contrary qualities in them, ſeeing they conſiſt but of one Element; they live many Ages before they die; but what is time in compariſon of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? They muſt return again into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>byſs of nothing. That thought afflicts them ſo much, that we have a hard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ask of it to comfort them poor ſouls.</p>
               <p>Our Fore-fathers the Philoſophers, ſpeaking to God Face to Face, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to him of the miſery of thoſe People; and God whoſe mercy is infinite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evealed to them that it was not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151429:13"/> to find a Remedy to that Evil. He informed them that in the ſame manner as Man by the Alliance that he hath contracted with God, has been partaker of Divini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y; ſo the <hi>Sy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phes, Gnomes, Nymphes,</hi> and <hi>Salamand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs,</hi> by the Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which they m ght co tract with Man, may be made pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality. Thus a <hi>Ny<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ph</hi> or <hi>Sylphide</hi> becom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pable of Immortality, and of the Bliſs to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich we aſpire; when ſhe is ſo happy as to be married to a <hi>Sage:</hi> and a <hi>Gnome</hi> or <hi>Sylphe</hi> ceaſes to be mortal ſo ſoon as ever he eſpouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s one of our Daughters.</p>
               <p>From thence ſpring the Error of the firſt Ages, of <hi>Tertullian, Juſtin Martyr, Lactantius, Cyprian, Cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt</hi> of <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xandria Athenagoras,</hi> a Chriſtian Philoſopher and generally of all the Writers of that Age. They learnt that thoſe elementary half men courted the Commerce of Maids; and from that they imagined that the Fall of the Angels was occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed onely, by the love which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained for Women. Some <hi>Gnomes</hi> deſirous of immortality, courted the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of our Daughters, and brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151429:13"/> them precious Stones, whereof they are naturally the Guardians: And theſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours thought, grounding their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion on the Book of <hi>Enoch,</hi> not rightly underſtood, that thoſe were the Snares which the Amorous Angels laid for our Women. In the beginning theſe Children of Heaven begot famous Gyants on the Daughters of Men, who fell in love with them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And the bad <hi>Cabaliſts, Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Philo</hi> (as all the Jews are ignorant) and after them the Authors whom I juſt now named, as well as <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Macrobius,</hi> have affirmed they were Angels, not knowing that they were <hi>Sylphes</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Elementary People, who by the name of the Children of <hi>Eloim,</hi> are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the Children of Men. In like manner, that which the wiſe <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> had the modeſty not to decide, in relation to the Addreſſes which thoſe who were called <hi>Faunes</hi> or <hi>Satyrs,</hi> made to the <hi>Affricans</hi> of his time; is cleared by what I have ſaid of the deſire that all thoſe Inhabitants of the Elements have to be allied with Men, as the onely means to attain to the Immortality which they want.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151429:14"/>
               <p>Ah! our <hi>Sages</hi> are far from imputing the Fall of the firſt Angels to the love of Women, no more than they ſubmit Men ſo much to the power of Devils, as to aſcribe to him the adventures of <hi>Nymphs</hi> and <hi>Sylphes,</hi> wherewith all Hiſtories abound. There was never any Crime in that Matter; it was onely <hi>Sylphes</hi> endeavouring to become Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. Their innocent Purſuits are ſo far from ſcandaliſing Philoſophers, that they have appeared to us ſo juſt, that we have all with one conſent reſolved to give our ſelves to no other Pleaſure but the immortalizing of <hi>Nymphs</hi> and <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phides.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God, God (cried I) what is this I hear? Is there no end of the f....? Yes, my Son (interrupted the Count) admire that there is no end of the Feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Philoſophers! Inſtead of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whoſe frail Charms are quickly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and are followed with ghaſtly Wrinkles, the <hi>Sages</hi> enjoy Beauties that never grow old, and whom they have the Glory to render immortal. Reflect on the Love and Gratitude of thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible Miſtreſſes: and with what eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151429:14"/> they deſire to pleaſe the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, who applies himſelf to procure them Immortality.</p>
               <p>Ah! Sir, I renounce (cried I once more.) Yes my Son (continued he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, without giving me leave to make an end) renounce the vain and periſhing pleaſures that are found amongſt Women; the Faireſt of them looks Ghaſtly, when compared to the meaneſt <hi>Sylphide:</hi> our <hi>Sage</hi> Embraces are never dogg'd with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the leaſt diſtaſte. Miſerable Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, how much are ye to be pitied, that ye cannot taſte of Philoſophical De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</p>
               <p>And miſerable Count of <hi>Gabalis</hi> (ſaid I with a tone made up of Anger and Compaſſion) let me at length tell you, that I renounce that diſtracted Wiſdom; that your Viſionary Philoſophy ſeems to me ridiculous, that I deteſt theſe abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Embraces that couple you to <hi>Sprights;</hi> and that I ſhake for fear, leaſt one or other of your pretended <hi>Sylphides</hi> haſten to carry you to Hell in the midſt of your tranſports; for fear that ſuch a worthy Gentleman as you are, ſhould at length perceive the folly of that fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtical
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151429:15"/> Zeal, and repent of ſo hainous a Crime.</p>
               <p>Ho, ho (anſwered he, ſtarting three or four ſteps back, and looking on me angrily) a Curſe on that untractable Spirit of thine. I confeſs his Carriage put me into a fright, but it was far worſe, when I ſaw, that drawing aſide, he pulled a Paper out of his Pocket, which I perceived at a diſtance to be full of Characters that I could not well diſcern. He read attentively, pelted and muttered to himſelf. I thought he was a raiſing ſome Spirits to deſtroy me, and repented a little of my inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Zeal. If I come off well at this bout (ſaid I) I'll never fear <hi>Cabaliſt</hi> more. I had fixed mine Eyes ſtedfaſtly upon him, as upon a Judge that was going to ſentence me to death; when I perceived his Countenance clear up again. It is hard for you (ſaid he laughing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning towards me) it is hard for you to kick againſt pricks, you are a Veſſel of Election. Heaven has deſtin'd you for the greateſt <hi>Cabaliſt</hi> of your Age. Here is the Figure of your Nativity, that cannot fail, if it happen not preſently
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151429:15"/> and by my means, it will be when your Retrograde <hi>Saturn</hi> ſhall think fit.</p>
               <p>Nay, God Sir, If it be my luck to become a <hi>Sage</hi> (ſaid I) no Man, I aſſure you ſhall ever have a hand in it, except the great <hi>Gabalis;</hi> but to ſpeak freely, I am ſomewhat afraid you'll find it no eaſie task, to perſwade me to this Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophick Gallantry. Is it then, becauſe you are ſo bad a Naturaliſt (replied he) as not to believe the Exiſtence of theſe People? I cannot tell (ſaid I) but I am ſtill of opinion that they are but <hi>Gob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi> in diſguiſe. Will you ſtill give greater credit to your Nurſe (anſwered he) than to Natural Reaſon; than to <hi>Plato, Pythagoras, Celſus, Pſellus, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clus, Porphyrius, Jamblichus, Plotinus, Triſmegiſtus, Noll us, Dorneus, Fluddus,</hi> than to the great <hi>Philippus Aurelius Theophraſtus Bombaſtus Paracelſus</hi> of <hi>Honeinhem;</hi> and all the reſt of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions?</p>
               <p>I'll believe you Sir (ſaid I) as much and more than all theſe Blades: But dear Sir, cannot you ſo order matters with your Brethren, that I be not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to melt away in love with theſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151429:16"/> Elementary Laſſes? Alas! (replied he) you are at your liberty, no Man is forced to love; but though few of the <hi>Sages</hi> are proof againſt their Charms, yet there have been ſome, who reſerving themſelves wholly to greater Matters (as you ſhall know hereafter) have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that honour to <hi>Nymphs.</hi> I'll be one of thoſe then (anſwered I) for indeed I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bring my ſelf to a reſolution to loſe time in uſing of the Ceremonies, which as I have heard a <hi>Prelat</hi> ſay, are neceſſary for obtaining the Commerce of thoſe <hi>Spirits.</hi> That <hi>Prelat</hi> knew not what he ſaid (replied the <hi>Count</hi>) for you ſhall one day ſee that they are not <hi>Spirits;</hi> and beſides, never did a <hi>Sage</hi> uſe either Ceremonies or Superſtition, for gaining the Familiarity of <hi>Spirits,</hi> nor of the <hi>People</hi> of whom we ſpeak.</p>
               <p>A <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>baliſt</hi> never acts but by Natural Principles; and if in our Books there be ſometimes hard Words, Characters and Fumigations to be found; that is onely to hide from the ignorant the Principles of Nature. Admire the ſimplicity of Nature in all her moſt wonderful Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations! and in that ſimplicity ſo great,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151429:16"/> ſo exact, and neceſſary an Harmony, that in ſpight of your Prejudices it will cure you of your weak Apprehenſions. What I am about to tell you, we teach thoſe of our Diſciples, whom we ſuffer not to enter into the innermoſt Sanctuary of Nature; and yet will not deprive of the Society of the Elementary People, out of compaſſion that we have for the ſame People.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Salamanders,</hi> as you perhaps al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready conceive, are compoſed of the moſt ſubtle parts of the Sphere of Fire, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>globated and organiſed, by the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the univerſal Fire (of which ſome time or other I will diſcourſe to you) ſo called, becauſe it is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of all the Motions of Nature. In the ſame manner the <hi>Sylphs</hi> are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of the pureſt atomes of Air, the <hi>Nymphs</hi> of the thinneſt particles of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and the <hi>Gnomes</hi> of the ſubtileſt parts of the Earth. <hi>Adam</hi> bore ſome propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with theſe ſo perfect Creatures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe being made up of the pureſt part of the four Elements; he contained in himſelf the perfections of theſe four kinds of People, and was their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151429:17"/> King. But when ſin had precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated him among the Excrements of the Elements (as you ſhall ſee ſome other time) the Harmony was untuned, and becoming groſs and impure, he bore no more proportion with thoſe ſo pure and ſubtile Subſtanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. What remedy to this evil? How is the Lute to be tuned again, and this loſt Soveraignty retrived? O Nature! Why art thou ſo little ſtudied? Do not you conceive, my Son, with what ſimplicity Nature can reſtore Man to the Bleſſings which he hath loſt?</p>
               <p>Alas! Sir (replied I) I am very igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in all theſe ſimplicities. But it is very eaſie however to be knowing in them (anſwered he.)</p>
               <p>If we would recover the Empire over the <hi>Salamanders,</hi> we muſt purifie and exalt the Element of Fire that is in us, and raiſe again the tone of that ſlacken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed String. There is no more to be done, but to concentrate the Fire of the World by concave mirrours in a Bowl of Glaſs; and this is the Operation which all the Ancients have religiouſly concealed, until Divine <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> revealed it In that Bowl there is a Solary
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151429:17"/> Powder made, which being of it ſelf purified from the mixture of other Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and being prepared according to Art, becomes in a very ſhort time a Sovereign Remedy to exalt the Fire that is in us; and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke us (if one may ſay ſo) become of an igneous Nature. Then do the Inhabitants of the Sphere of Fire become our inferiors, and raviſhed to ſee our mutual Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reſtored, and that we are become like to them, they have the ſame love and friendſhip for us that they have for their own kind; all the reſpect which they owe to the Image and Vicegerent of their Creator, and all the care, that the deſire of obtaining the immorta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity which they want, by our means, can make them excogitate. The truth is, as being more ſubtile and pure than thoſe of the other Elements, they live very long; ſo they are not ſo ſolicitous in demanding Immortality from the <hi>Sages.</hi> You may make uſe of one of thoſe, my Son, if the averſion you talk of laſt always: probably you ſhall never hear her ſpeak one word of that which you are ſo much afraid of.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:151429:18"/>
               <p>The eaſe is not the ſame with the <hi>Sylphs, Gnomes,</hi> and <hi>Nymphs,</hi> for ſeeing, as being ſhorter lived, they ſtand more in need of us; ſo their Familiarity is more eaſily obtained. There is no more to be done for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but to ſtop a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle full of cong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obated Air, Water, or Earth, and ſet it for a month in the Sun; and then to ſeparate the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments according to Art, which above all is moſt eaſie to be done in the Water and Earth. It is wonder, what a ſtrange Load-ſtone each of theſe Elements pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified are, to attract <hi>Nymphs, Sylphes,</hi> and <hi>Gnomes.</hi> As little almoſt as nothing taken of it daily for the ſpace of ſome months, will let you ſee in the Air the republick volant of <hi>Sylphs;</hi> the <hi>Nymphs</hi> coming in crouds to the Shore; and the Guardians of Treaſure opening Shop and laying out their Wealth. So that without Characters, Ceremonies, and barbarous Words, one becomes abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute over all thoſe People. They de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand no Worſhip from a <hi>Sage</hi> whom they know to be nobler than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Thus venerable Nature teaches her Children to repair the Elements by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151429:18"/> the Elements. Thus is Harmony re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored. Thus does Man recover his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Empire, and can do all things in the Elements, without the Devil or black Art: You ſee now, my Son, that the <hi>Sages</hi> are more in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cent than you imagine. What do you ſay?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I admire you, Sir,</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to fear that you will make me turn Apothecary. Ah! God forbid, my Child</hi> (cried he) <hi>your Nativity has not deſtin'd you for ſuch trifles. On the contrary, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge you to trouble your Head about di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilling; I have told you that the</hi> Sages <hi>teach ſuch things onely to thoſe whom they will not admit into their Society. You ſhall have all theſe advantages, and many others more glorious and agreeable, by Philoſophick Procedures of a far different Nature. I have on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y told you of theſe ways, that I might let you ſee the innocence of this Philoſophy, and cure you of your panick fears.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thanks be to God, Sir</hi> (anſwered I) <hi>my fear is not ſo great now, as it was a while ago; and though I be not as yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lved to embrace the offer that you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to me with the</hi> Salamanders: <hi>yet I
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151429:19"/> have ſtill the curioſity to be informed, how you have learnt that theſe</hi> Nymphs <hi>and</hi> Sylphs <hi>do die? In troth</hi> (replied he) <hi>they tell us ſo, and we ſee them die. How can you ſee them die</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>ſince your Commerce renders them im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ortal. You had ſaid ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what</hi> (anſwered he) <hi>if the</hi> Sages <hi>were as many in number as thoſe People are; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, a great many of them had rather die than to run the riſque of being as mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable as they ſee the Devils are, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to attain to Immortality. It is the Devil that puts theſe thoughts into the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r Heads, for he does all he can to hinder theſe poor Creatures from becoming Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal by our Alliance. So that I look, and you ought my Son, to look upon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion which you have to it, as a moſt perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious temptation and uncharitable inclination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But further, as to the Death you have been ſpeaking of, What was it that obliged the <hi>Oracle</hi> of <hi>Apollo</hi> to ſay, That all who ſpake in <hi>Oracles</hi> were dead as well as himſelf; as <hi>Porphiry</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports? And what meant that voice, d'ye think, which was heard over all the Coaſts of <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſo terrified thoſe that were at Sea? <hi>The great Pan is dead.</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:151429:19"/> It was the People of the Air, who gave advice to the People of the Water, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at the Chief and moſt Aged of the <hi>Sylphes</hi> was juſt then expired.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When that voice was heard</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>I think the World adored</hi> Pan <hi>and the</hi> Nymphs. <hi>Theſe Gentlemen then, whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce you preach to me, were the</hi> Pagan <hi>Gods?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is true, my Son</hi> (replied he) <hi>the</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <hi>are far from thinking that the Devil had ever the power to make himſelf be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dored; he is too miſerable and weak ever to have had that Satisfaction and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: but he may have perſwaded thoſe Gueſts of the Elements to appear to Men, and to procure Temples to be dedicated to them; who by the Natural Dominion that each of them have over the Element they poſſeſs; they troubled the Air and Sea, ſhook the Earth, and ſent Thunder and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at their pleaſure: inſomuch that it was eaſie for them to be taken for Deities, ſo long as the Supream Being neglected the Salvation of the Nations. But the Devil obtained not all the advantage that he expected from his malice: for it came to paſs by that, that</hi> Pan, <hi>the</hi> Nymphs, <hi>and other Elementary People, having found a means to change
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151429:20"/> that commerce of Worſhip into a commerce of Love (for you remember th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t among the Ancients,</hi> Pan <hi>was the King of thoſe Gods, who were called</hi> Incubus's, <hi>and made love to Maids) many of the</hi> Pagans <hi>eſcaped the ſnares of the Devil; and ſhall not burn in Hell Flames.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I underſtood you not, Sir</hi> (ſaid I.) <hi>You will not underſtand me</hi> (continued he in a jearing tone and ſmiling) <hi>this is above your reach, and indeed ſurpaſſes the reach of all your Doctors, who know not what true Natural Philoſophy means. I'll tell you the great Myſtery of all that part of Philoſophy which concerns the Elements, and which (if you love your ſelf) will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly remove that ſo unphiloſophical repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy which you have teſtified to me this very day. Know then, my Son, and divulge not this great</hi> Arcanum <hi>to any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ignorant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Know that as the</hi> Sylphs <hi>acquire Immortalily, by an Alliance which they contract with Men who are predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated; even ſo Men, who have no right to Eternal Glory; thoſe Wretches to whom Immortality is but a fatal advantage; for whom the Meſſias was not ſent.....</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hold, hold, ye Gentlemen of the</hi> Cabal
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151429:20"/> 
                  <hi>are</hi> Calviniſts <hi>and</hi> Presbiterians <hi>then?</hi> (ſaid I interrupting him.) <hi>We know not what that means, my Child</hi> (replied he briskly) <hi>and we ſcorn to inform our ſelves about the differences of Sects and Religions, with which the ignorant are infatuated. We ſtick to the Ancient R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ligi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n of our Fore-fathers the Philoſophers, wherein I muſt needs ſometime or other inſtruct you. But to return to the purpoſe, thoſe Men whoſe ſad Immortality will prove but ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry; thoſe accurſed Children whom the ſupream Father hath forſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ken, have this relief ſtill, that they may become Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, by matching with Elementary People. So that you ſee that the</hi> Sages <hi>hazard nothing for Eternity; if they are predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, they have the Satisfaction, when they leave the Body, to carry to Heaven with them the</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ylphide <hi>or</hi> Nymph <hi>whom they have immortalized; and if they are not prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, the Commerce of the</hi> Sylphide <hi>renders their Soul mortal, and delivers them from the horrours of the ſecond Death. Thus all the</hi> Nymphs, <hi>who were allied wiih the</hi> Pagans, <hi>eſcaped the Clutches of the Devil, Thus the</hi> Sages, <hi>or the Friends of the Wiſe, to whom God puts it in our hearts
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151429:21"/> to communicate any of the four Elementary Secrets (which I have pretty near diſcovered to you) free themſelves from the danger of damnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In ſober ſadneſs, Sir (cried I, not daring to put him out of humour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and judging it fit to forbear tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him openly my thoughts, until that he had diſcovered to me all the Secrets of his Cabal; which by that pattern I concluded muſt needs be very odd and pleaſant) In ſober ſadneſs, you carry Wiſdom very far! and you had reaſon to ſay that it would ſurpaſs the reach of all our Doctors. I am truly of opinion that this is alſo above the reach of all our Magiſtrates: and that if they could find out who they are that make their eſcape from the Devil by this means (as ignorance is always unjuſt) they would take the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils part againſt thoſe Fugitives, and trunch them ſeverely.</p>
               <p>And it is for that reaſon (replied the Count) that I have recommended, and do religiouſly recommend to you Secrecy. Your Judges are ſtrange Men! they condemn a moſt innocent Action as
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151429:21"/> a moſt hainous Crime. What barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? to cauſe burn thoſe two Prieſts whom the Prince of <hi>Mirandula</hi> ſays he knew; each of whom had his <hi>Sylphide</hi> for the ſpace of forty years! What in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity was it to have put to death <hi>Jean Hervillier,</hi> who for the ſpace of thirty ſix years, laboured in the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talizing of a <hi>Gnome!</hi> And how ignorant was <hi>Bodinus,</hi> to call her a Witch; and to take occaſion from her adventure, to authorize the vulgar Fancies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Sorcerers; by a Book no leſs impertinent than that of his Republick is rational.</p>
               <p>But it is late, and I conſider not that you have not as yet eaten any thing. You ſpeak for your ſelf, Sir (ſaid I) for my own part I could hear you on till too morrow without trouble. Ah! for me (replied he laughing and going towards the door) it is evident that you know but little what Philoſophy is. The <hi>Sages</hi> eat only for pleaſure, and never f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r neceſſity. I had a quite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Notion of Wiſdom (anſwered I) I thought that a <hi>Sage</hi> ought not to eat but to ſatisfie neceſſity. You a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abuſe
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151429:22"/> your ſelf (ſaid the Count) how long d'ye think our <hi>Sages</hi> can hold out without eating? What can I tell (ſaid I) <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as</hi> faſted forty days, your <hi>Sages</hi> without doubt come ſome few days ſhort of them. A mighty matter indeed (replied he) the wiſeſt Man that ever was, the divine and almoſt adorable <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> aſſures us that he has ſeen a great many <hi>Sages,</hi> who have ſpent twenty years without eating the leaſt thing imaginable. He himſelf, before he attained to the Monarchy of Wiſdom, whereof we have juſtly given him the Scepter; lived ſeveral years without taking any thing but half a Scruple of <hi>Solar Quinteſſence.</hi> And if you would have the pleaſure to make any one live without eating; you have no more to do but to prepare the Earth, as I have told you may be prepared by the Society of <hi>Gnomes.</hi> That Earth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing applied to the Navil, and renewed when it is too dry, makes one without the leaſt trouble, diſpenſe with eating and drinking: as the Candid <hi>Paracelſus</hi> affirms he had the experience for the ſpace of ſix Months.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:151429:22"/>
               <p>But the uſe of the Catholick Cabali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Medicine frees us much better from the troubleſome neceſſities, to which Nature ſubjects the Ignorant. We eat but when we pleaſe, and all the ſuperfluity of our Victuals evaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by inſenſible tranſpiration, we are never aſhamed of being Men. With that he held his Peace, perceiving that we were near our Servants. So we went to a Village to take a ſlight Bait, according to the cuſtom of the Hero's of Philoſophy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="conference">
               <head>The Third Conference about Secret Sciences.</head>
               <p>After Dinner we returned to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth. I was penſive, and the pity that I had of the Counts Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, which I perceived would be very hard for me to cure, ſuffered me not to divert my ſelf with what he had ſaid, ſo much as I would have done, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f there had been any hopes of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng him to his Wits. I ranſanck'd An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151429:23"/> to find ſome Objection which he could not anſwer; for to alledge the Opinions of the Church to him, was in vain, ſeeing he told me that he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered only to the Ancient Religion of his Fore-fathers the Philoſophers; and to attempt to convince a <hi>Cabaliſt</hi> by reaſon, was a long and tedious task: and beſides, I had no mind to diſpute againſt a Man whoſe Principles as yet were not altogether known to me.</p>
               <p>It came into my mind, that what he had told me of the falſe Gods, to whom he ſubſtituted <hi>Sylphs</hi> and other Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary People, might be refuted by the <hi>Pagan Oracles,</hi> which the Scripture calls in all places <hi>Devils</hi> and not <hi>Sylphs.</hi> But ſeeing I knew not whether in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the <hi>Cabal</hi> the Count would not attribute the Reſponſes of the <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> to ſome Natural Cauſe, I thought it pertinent firſt to know what his thoughts were as to that.</p>
               <p>He gave me occaſion to engage him in the Subject; for turning towards the Garden, before we entered the Labyrinth; This Garden looks very well (ſaid he) and theſe Statua's make a fair Show.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151429:23"/> The Cardinal (anſwered I) who cauſed them to be brought hither, entertained a fancy that ſuited ill with his great Parts. He thought that moſt of thoſe Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ua's rendered heretofore <hi>Oracles:</hi> and upon that he paid very dear for them. That is the infirmity of many People (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Count) Ignorance produces daily a kind of moſt Criminal Idolatry; ſeeing with ſo much care Men preſerve and preciouſly eſteem the Idols which they believe the Devil heretofore made uſe of to make himſelf be adored. Good God will it never be known in the World that from the beginning of all Ages thou haſt made thine Enemies thy Foot-ſtool; and that thou holdeſt the Devils Priſoners under Chains of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? That blame-worthy curioſity of making Collections of thoſe pretended Organs of the Devils, might become innocent, my Son, if Men would be perſwaded, that Angels of Darkneſs were never ſuffered to ſpeak in <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not think (ſaid I interrupting him) that this Doctrine would eaſily paſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the curious; but perhaps it
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151429:24"/> might among the Wits. For it was late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decided in a Conference held pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely on that Subject, by the Wits of the firſt rank, that all the pretended <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> were but Tricks of the covetous Heatheniſh Prieſts, or an Artifice of the State-Policy of Princes.</p>
               <p>Was it (ſaid the Count) the <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans</hi> that were ſent in Embaſſy to your King, who held that Conference; and ſo decided that Queſtion? No, Sir (anſwered I.) What Religion were thoſe Gentlemen of then (replied he) ſeeing they make no account of Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which in ſo many places makes mention of ſo many different <hi>Oracles?</hi> and eſpecially of the <hi>Pythons,</hi> who had their Reſidence, and rendered their Reſponſes in the parts appointed for the multiplication of the Image of God? I ſpake (anſwered I) of all thoſe Belly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talkers, and I inſtanced to the Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that King <hi>Saul</hi> baniſhed them his Kingdom, where nevertheleſs he ſtill found one the night before he died; whoſe Voice had the wonderful power to raiſe <hi>Samuel</hi> at his deſire, and for his Ruin. But theſe Learned Men, for all
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151429:24"/> that, denied abſolutely that there were ever any <hi>Oracles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If Scripture had no influence upon them (ſaid the Count) they ſhould have been convinced by all Antiquity; wherein it was eaſie to have ſhew'd them a thouſand miraculous inſtances. So many Virgins with-child of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny of Mortals, who were delivered of the good or bad hap of thoſe that conſulted them. Why don't ye alledge <hi>Chryſoſtom, Origen,</hi> and <hi>Oecumenius?</hi> who make mention of thoſe Divine Men, whom the <hi>Greeks</hi> called <hi>Engaſtrimandres,</hi> whoſe Prophetick Bellies articulated ſo famous <hi>Oracles.</hi> And if your Blades care neither for the Scripture nor the Fathers, they are to be convinced by thoſe miraculous Maids, who trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed themſelves into Doves, and under that ſhape rendered the famous <hi>Oracles</hi> of <hi>Dodo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a's Doves.</hi> Or you may ſay, to the Glory of your Nation, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here have been heretofore in <hi>Gallia,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lluſtrious Maids, who metamorphoſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hemſelves into all Figures, at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leaſure of thoſe who conſulted them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd who beſides the famous <hi>Oracles</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:151429:25"/> which they rendered, had a wonderful Empire over the Floods, and a ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Authority over the moſt Incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>They would have termed all theſe fair proofs Apocryphal (ſaid I.) What, does Antiquity render them ſuſpected? (replied he) you might then have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to them the <hi>Oracles</hi> which are daily rendered. And where in all the World? (ſaid I.) At <hi>Paris</hi> (anſwered h e.) At <hi>Paris!</hi> (cried I.) Yes at <hi>Paris</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued he.) Are you a Maſter in <hi>Iſrael</hi> and know not that? Do not Men daily conſult <hi>Aquatick Oracles</hi> in Water-glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or Baſins; and <hi>Aereal Oracles</hi> in Looking-glaſſes, and on the Hands of Virgins? Are not loſt Beads and ſtollen Watches thus recovered? Do not they likewiſe hear News from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Countreys, and ſee abſent Friends? Alas! Sir, Why do you tell me of thoſe things (ſaid I.) I tell you (replied he) what I am ſure happens daily, and which might be eaſily proved by a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Eye-witneſſes. I don't believe that Sir (ſaid I) the Magiſtrates would make an Example of ſuch an Action
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151429:25"/> and would not ſuffer Idolatry..... How quick you are! (ſaid the Count in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting me.) There is not ſo much hurt in that, as you imagine; and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence will never permit that Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Philoſophy, which hath eſcaped the lamentable Shipwrack that Truth hath made, to be extirpated. If there ſtill remain among the People ſome foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtep of the dreadful power of Divine Names, are you of the opinion that it ſhould be extirpated? And that Men ſhould loſe the reſpect and veneration which is due to the great Name <hi>AGLA,</hi> that worketh all theſe Wonders, even when it is invoked by the Ignorant and Sinners; and which would produce Wonders of another Nature in a Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtick Mouth? If you would have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced thoſe Gentlemen of the truth of <hi>Oracles;</hi> you needed but to have exalted your Imagination and Faith, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards the Eaſt, cried with a loud voice <hi>AG.....</hi> Hold, good Sir (ſaid I) I would have been very loath to have made ſuch a kind of Argument to ſo worthy Gentlemen as I was with; they would have taken me for a Phanatick:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151429:26"/> for aſſuredly they believe not a word of all that: and though I had known the Cabaliſtick Operation you ſpeak of, it would not have ſucceeded in my Mouth; for I have leſs Faith than they. Well, well (ſaid the Count) if you have none, we ſhall procure you ſome. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, if you thought that your Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men would not have believed what they may daily ſee at <hi>Paris,</hi> you might have cited to them a ſtory of very freſh date: The <hi>Oracle</hi> which <hi>Celius Rhodiginus</hi> ſays himſelf ſaw, about the end of the laſt Age, rendered by that extraordinary Man, who ſpoke; and fore-told things to come by the ſame Organ as <hi>Eurycles</hi> in <hi>Plutarch</hi> did. I would not cite <hi>Rhodiginus</hi> (anſwered I) it would have been a Pedantick Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and beſides, they would not have failed to have told me that that Man was poſſeſſed.</p>
               <p>That would have been ſaid moſt Monkiſhly (replied he.) Sir (ſaid I, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting him) for all the Cabaliſtick Averſion which I perceive you have to Monks, I cannot but be on their ſide in this particular. I think it may be
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151429:26"/> more ſaf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly denied that ever there was any <hi>Oracle,</hi> than to deny that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſpoke in them: For in fine, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Divines.... For in fine (ſaid he, interrupting me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) do not Divines agree that the Learned <hi>Sambethe</hi> the oldeſt of the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>byles</hi> was the Daughter of <hi>Noah?</hi> Puh! what of all that (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied I.) Does not <hi>Plutarch</hi> (anſwered he) ſay that the moſt Ancient <hi>Sybill</hi> was the firſt that rendered <hi>Oracles</hi> at <hi>Delphos?</hi> That Spirit which <hi>Sambethe</hi> lodged in her Breaſt was not then at Devil, nor her <hi>Apollo</hi> a falſe god; ſeeing Idolatry did not begin till long after the Diviſion of Tongues: and it would be very unlikely to attribute the Sacred Books of the <hi>Sybills,</hi> and all the Proofs of the True Religion, which the Fathers have drawn from them, to the Father of Lies: And then my Child, (continued he ſmiling) it is not your part, to diſſolve the Marriage which a great Cardinal made betwixt <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Sybllia;</hi> nor to accuſe that Learned Man of having unequally yoked a great Prophet and an accurſed Sorcereſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. For either <hi>David</hi> confirms the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151429:27"/> Evidence of the <hi>Sybill,</hi> or the <hi>Sybill</hi> weakens the Authority of <hi>David.</hi> I pray you Sir (ſaid I, interrupting him) to the point again and be ſerious.</p>
               <p>With all my heart (ſaid he) on con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition you will not accuſe me of being too ſerious. Is the Devil, in your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, ever divided againſt himſelf? And does he at any time act againſt his own Intereſts? Why not (ſaid I.) Why not? (ſaid he) becauſe he whom <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſo happily and magnificently calls the Reaſon of God, thinks it not proper. Satan is never divided againſt Satan. It follows then, That either the Devil never ſpoke in <hi>Oracles,</hi> or that he hath never ſpoke againſt his Intereſt. It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows then, that if the <hi>Oracles</hi> have ſpoken againſt the intereſts of the Devil, it was not the Devil that ſpake in the <hi>Oracles.</hi> But could not God have forced the Devil (ſaid I) to give teſtimony to the Truth, and to ſpeak againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf? But (replied he) if God hath not forced him. Ah! in that caſe (ſaid I) you'll have more reaſon than the Monks.</p>
               <p>Let us ſee then, continued he, and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151429:27"/> that we may proceed invincibly and with ſincerity; I will not adduce the teſtimonies of the <hi>Oracles</hi> which the Fathers of the Church cite; though I be perſwaded of the veneration which you have for theſe great Men. Their Religion and the Intereſt which they had in the Matter, might have prejudiced them, and their love to the truth might have ſo prevailed with them, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it poor and naked in their Age, they might have borrowed ſome Clothing and Ornament for it from Falſhood it ſelf: They were Men, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence might, according to the Maxime of the Prophet of the Synagogue, have been unfaithful Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>I will take then a Man, who cannot be ſuſpected in this Cauſe: A <hi>Pagan,</hi> and a <hi>Pagan</hi> of another kind than <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi> or the <hi>Epicureans;</hi> a <hi>Pagan</hi> infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated (as he is) with Gods and Devils without number, beyond meaſure ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, a great Magician, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending ſo to be; and by conſequence a great favourer of Devils, it is <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrius.</hi> Here are ſome of the <hi>Oracles</hi> which he reports word for word.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="oracle">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:151429:28"/>
                     <head>ORACLE.</head>
                     <p>ABove the Celeſtial Fire there is an incorruptible, ever ſparkling Flame, the Source of Life, the Fountain of all Stars, and the Principle of all Things. That Flame produces every thing, and nothing periſhes but what it conſumes. It makes it ſelf known by it ſelf; this Fire can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in no place; it is without body and matter; it incompaſſes the Heavens, and from it comes forth a little Spark, which makes the Fire of the Sun, Moon, and Stars. This is what I know of God; inquire not after more, for it is above thy reach, how wiſe ſoever thou mayſt be. Know moreover, that an unjuſt and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man cannot be hid from God. Neither cunning nor excuſe can
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151429:28"/> conceal any thing from his piercing Eyes. All is filled with God; God is every where.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>You well perceive (my Son) that this</hi> Oracle <hi>looks not too much like the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. At leaſt (anſwered I) the Devil ſteps a little out of his rode in it. Here is another (ſaid he) which preaches ſtill better.</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="oracle">
                  <body>
                     <head>ORACLE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THere is in God an immenſe depth of Flame; yet the Heart of Man ſhould not fear to touch that adorable Fire, nor to be touched by it; it ſhall not be conſumed by that ſo gentle Fire, the mild and peaceable heat where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of cauſes the Conjunction, Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and Duration of the World. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſubſiſts but by this Fire, which is God himſelf. He is not begotten, he has no Mother, he knows all things, and can be taught
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151429:29"/> nothing; he is immutable in his purpoſes, and his Name is ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, this is God; for as for us, who are his Meſſengers, we are but a little particle of God.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Well now! What ſay you to this? I ſay of both (anſwered I) that God can force the Father of Lies to give teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the Truth. Come here is a third (replied the Count) that will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move your Scruple.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALas</hi> Tripodes! <hi>Weep, and make the Funeral Oration of your</hi> Apollo; <hi>he is mortal, he is going to die. He extinguiſheth, becauſe the Light of the Coeleſtial Flame makes him extinct.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You well perceive (my Child) that whoever he be that ſpeaks in theſe <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles,</hi> and who ſo well explains to <hi>Pagans</hi> the Eſſence, Unity, Immmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, and Eternity of God; he confeſſes that he is Mortal, and that he is but a ſpark of God. It is not then the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil that ſpeaks, becauſe he is Immortal, and God would not force him to ſay that he is not ſo. It is agreed that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151429:29"/> is not divided againſt himiſelf. Is that the way for him to be adored, to ſay, That there is but one God? He ſays that he is Mortal; how long is it ſince the Devil was ſo humble as to ſtrip himſelf even of his Natural Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? You ſee then, my Son, that if the Principle of him, who by Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence is called the God of Knowledge, hold Good; the Devil can never have ſpoken in the <hi>Oracles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if it be not the Devil (ſaid I) either in a frollick tell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng a Lie, when he calls himſelf Mortal; or ſpeaking the Truth by force, when he ſpeaks of God; to what then will your <hi>Cabal</hi> aſcribe all the <hi>Oracles,</hi> which ye main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to have been really delivered? Is it to an exhalation of the Earth, as <hi>Ariſtotle, Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Plutarch</hi> affirm? Not ſo my Child, (ſaid the Count) t anks to the Sacred <hi>Cabal,</hi> I'me not ſo far out of my Wits yet. <hi>How!</hi> (replied I) <hi>hold you that then to be a Fantaſtical O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion? It is maintained though by men of good ſenſe.</hi> They are not ſo in this point, my Son <hi>(continued he)</hi> and it is impoſſible that all that hath been done
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151429:30"/> in Oracles, can be attributed to Exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: For Example, That Man, in <hi>Tacitus,</hi> who in a Dream appeared to the Prieſts of a Temple of <hi>Hercules</hi> in <hi>Armenia,</hi> and commanded them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide Dogs and Horſes to go a Hunting. Thus far it might have been Exhalati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but when at Night thoſe Dogs and Horſes returned almoſt ſpent, and the Quivers empty of Arrows, and that next day there were as many Beaſts found dead in the Forreſt, as there were Arrows in the Quivers; this you ſee could not be Exhalation. And far leſs it was the Devil; for it would be a very unreaſonable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabaliſtick Notion of the Miſery of the Enemy of God, to think that he is permitted to take his pleaſure in Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Hind or Hare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To what does the ſacred Cabal then</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>attribute the matter? Hold a little</hi> (anſwered he) <hi>before I diſcover to you that Myſtery, I muſt diſpoſſeſs you of a prejudice that you may entertain as to that pretended Exhalation; for it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me that you emphatically cited</hi> Ariſtotle, Plutarch, <hi>and</hi> Cicero. <hi>You
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151429:30"/> may likewiſe cite</hi> Jamblichus, <hi>wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r all he was a Man of ſo great parts, was ſometime in that Error; which he quickly forſook, when he had examined the Matter more narrowly in the Book of My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Peter <hi>of</hi> Apoua, Pomponatius, Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, Sirenius, <hi>and</hi> Lucilio Vanino, <hi>are over-joyed in finding that evaſion amongſt ſome of the Ancients. All theſe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Wits, who ſpeaking of Divine Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſay rather what they deſire, than what they know; will allow nothing ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural in Oracles, lest they ſhould be forced to acknowledge ſomewhat above man. They are afraid we ſhould lead them up, as by a</hi> Jacob's Ladder, <hi>to G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, whom they fear to know by the ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ps and degrees of ſpiritual creatures; but had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make themſelves one, to deſcend by into the Abyſs of Nothing; inſtead of lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves up to heaven, they dig down into the earth; and inſtead of ſearching in the beings, that are ſuperiour to man, the cauſe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe tranſports, that raiſe him above himſelf, and render him a kind of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ity: they weakly aſcribe to feeble Exhalations that vertue of penetrating in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151429:31"/> the future, of diſcovering hidden things, and of ſoaring up to the highest ſecrets of the Divine Eſſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Such is the miſery of Man, when he is poſſeſſed with a ſpirit of contradiction, and an humour of thinking otherwiſe than other men do! He is ſo far from attaining his ends, that he intangles and fetters him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. Theſe Libertines will not ſubject Man to ſubſtances leſs material than himſelf, and yet ſubject him to an Exhalation: and never conſidering that there is no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogy betwixt that Chimerical ſteam and the ſoul of Man; betwixt that vapor and things future; betwixt that frsvolous cauſe and thoſe miraeulous Effects: It is enough for them to be ſingular, to make them think themſelves reaſonable; and to deny ſpirits, that they may ſet up for men of ſpirit and wit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You are much offended at ſingularity then, Sir?</hi> (ſaid I, interrupting him.) Ah! my Son <hi>(anſwered he)</hi> it is the Plague of a good Judgment; and the ſtumbling-block of the greateſt Wits. <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> for all he was ſo great a Logician, could not avoid the ſnare, into which a conceit of ſingularity
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151429:31"/> leads thoſe who are ſo violently acted by it as he was: He could not <hi>(I ſay)</hi> avoid tripping and puzzling himſelf in his reaſonings. In his Book of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Animals, and in his <hi>Ethicks,</hi> he ſays, <hi>That the ſpirit and mind of Man comes to him from without, and that it is not tranſmitted from Father to Son; and from the ſpirituality of the operations of our Soul; he concludes it to be of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Nature than the Material Body which it inſpires, the groſsnoſs whereof does but offuſcate Speculations, far from producing them.</hi> Blind <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſeeing according to your opinion our material part cannot be the ſource of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual thoughts, how do you fancy that a weak Exhalation can be the Fountain of ſublime Speculations, and of the high Flight of the Pythians, who ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Oracles. You well perceive <hi>(my Child)</hi> how that great Wit trips, and that his ſingularity makes him loſe himſelf. <hi>You reaſon very exactly, Sir,</hi> (ſaid I, raviſhed to find that he ſpoke in effect to very good purpoſe; and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that his folly might not prove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable) <hi>God grant that.....</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:151429:32"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> an Author otherwiſe ſo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid <hi>(continued hc, interrupting me)</hi> is to be pitied in his Dialogue, Why the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles have ceaſed. He makes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf convincing Objections, which he does not ſolve. Why does not he then anſwer what is objected to him; that if it be an Exhalation which occaſions that tranſport, then all that approach the Prophetick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tool, ſhould be ſeiſed with Enthuſiaſme, and not a ſingle Maid, who muſt be alſo a Virgin. But how can that Vapour articulate a Voice in the Belly. Moreover that Exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a natural and neceſſary Agent, and ought always to produce regularly the ſame Effect? Why is that Maid then never inſpired, but when ſhe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted? And what is more urging, why has the Earth left off to ſend out ſuch Divine Vapours? Is it leſs Earth than it was? Does it receive other Influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Are there other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eas and other Rivers? Who has then ſtopped the Pores, or changed the Nature there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of?</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151429:32"/>
               <p>I wonder that <hi>Pomponatius, Lucilius,</hi> and the reſt of the Libertines, ſhould have followed the Notion of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and yet abandoned the way he takes to explain himſelf. He ſpoke more judiciouſly than <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> for he was a man indeed of good judgement, and not knowing what to make of all thoſe Oracles, after a long and tedious uncertainty, he at length fixed upon this, <hi>That that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halation which he believed came out of the Earth, was a moſt Divine Spirit,</hi> So that he aſcribed to the <hi>Deity thoſe extraordinary agitations and Prophetick Raptures of the Prieſts of Apollo. That Divining Vapour</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>is a Breath, and a moſt holy and divine Spirit. Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponatius, Lucilius,</hi> and the Modern A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, like not thoſe wayes of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which ſuppoſe a Deity. <hi>Theſe Exhalations</hi> (ſay they) <hi>were of the nature of thoſe Vapours which infeſt Melancholick People, who ſpeak Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages which they underſtand not.</hi> But <hi>Fernelius</hi> confutes theſe impious men very well, by proving that Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, which is a peccant Humour,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151429:33"/> cannot occaſion that variety of Tongues, which is one of the wonderfulleſt Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Conſideration, and an Artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Expreſſion of our Thoughts. He hath nevertheleſs but imperfectly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided the Matter, when he ſubſcribes to <hi>Pſellus,</hi> and to all thoſe who have not been ſufficiently endowed with our holy Philoſophy; for not knowing what cauſe to give for ſuch ſurprizing Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, like Women and Monks, he hath attributed them to the Devil. <hi>To whom are they then to be attributed?</hi> (ſaid I.) <hi>I have long waited for that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baliſtick Secret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> himſelf hath very well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> and he would have done well to have held to thar. That irregular way of Speaking by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly Organ, being baſe and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Majeſty of the Gods <hi>(ſays the Pagan)</hi> and what the Oracles ſaid, ſurpaſſing likewiſe: the power of the Soul of Man; they have done great Service to Philoſophy; who have pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a kind of Mortal Creatures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Gods and Man, to whom may be aſcribed all that ſurpaſſes the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151429:33"/> weakneſs of Man, and comes not near the greatneſs of the Deities.</p>
               <p>That is the Opinion of all the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Philoſophy. The <hi>Platoniſts</hi> and <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoreans</hi> learnt it from the <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and thoſe from <hi>Joſeph</hi> and the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who dwelt in <hi>AEgypt</hi> before they paſſed the <hi>Red Sea.</hi> The <hi>Hebrews</hi> called thoſe Subſtances which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Angels and Men, <hi>Sadaim;</hi> and the <hi>Greeks</hi> tranſpoſing the Syllables, and adding but one Letter, call them <hi>Dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monas.</hi> Theſe <hi>Demons</hi> amongſt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Philoſophers, are an Aereal Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, bearing rule over the Elements, mortal, generative, but unknown in this Age by thoſe who ſearch little for Truth in its ancient Habitations; that is to ſay, in the <hi>Cabal</hi> and <hi>Theology</hi> of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> who had the particular Art of Entertaining that Aereal Nation, and converſing with the Inhabitants of the Air.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You are at your Sylphs again, I fancy, Sir,</hi> (ſaid I interrupting him.) Yes, my Son <hi>(continued he)</hi> the <hi>Jewiſh Teraphim</hi> was onely the Ceremony that was to be obſerved for that Commerce: and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151429:34"/> that Jew <hi>Micah,</hi> who in the Book of <hi>Judges</hi> complains that they had carried away his Gods, laments only the loſs of the little Statue; wherein the Sylphs converſed with him. The Gods that <hi>Rachel</hi> ſtole from her Father, were alſo a <hi>Teraphim<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Micah</hi> and <hi>Laban</hi> are not accuſed of Idolatry, and <hi>Jacob</hi> would have been loath to have lived Fourteen years with an Idolater, or to have married his Daughter. It vvas but a Commerce of Sylphs; and vve know by Tradition that the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue held that Commerce to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and that <hi>David</hi>'s Wife's Idol was only a <hi>Teraphim,</hi> by means whereof ſhe entertained a Correſpondence with the Elementary People: for you may very well conceive, that the Prophet according to Gods own heart, would never have ſuffered Idolatry in his Houſe Whileſt for puniſhment of the firſt ſin, God ſlighted the World, theſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Nations took delight to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain to Men in Oracles what they knew of God; to teach them to live morally; to give them moſt wiſe and ſound Counſels; ſuch as are to be ſeen
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151429:34"/> in great numbers in <hi>Plutarch</hi> and all the Hiſtorians: But ſo ſoon as God took pity on the world, and would himſelf become its Teacher, theſe little Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with-drew; and from thence came the ſilence of the Oracles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The reſult of all your Diſcourſe Sir,</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>is that there have been certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Oracles, and that they were rendered by Sylphs: who render them ſtill daily in Glaſſes or Mirors.</hi> Sylphs or Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Gnomes, or Undians <hi>(replied the Count.) If it be ſo, Sir</hi> (anſwered I) <hi>all your Elementary People are an<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ill-bred Pack.</hi> And why? <hi>(ſaid he.) Why</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>can there be greater cheating and jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the World, than thoſe Reſponſes of double meaning which they alwayes gave.</hi> Alwayes <hi>(replied he.)</hi> Ha! not always. The Sylphide who appeared to that <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and foretold him, <hi>That he ſhould one day return thither with the Dignity of Pro-conſul.</hi> Did ſhe ſpeak very obſcurely? And does not <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſay, <hi>That the thing happened as ſhe had fore-told?</hi> That Inſcription and thoſe famous Statues in the Spaniſh Hiſtory, which informed the Unfortunate King,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151429:35"/> 
                  <hi>Roderigo, That his curioſity and inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence ſhould one day be puniſhed by me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cloathed and armed as they were; and that thoſe black men ſhould invade</hi> Spain, <hi>and reign long in it.</hi> Could any thing be clearer than that, and did not the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect juſtifie the truth that very ſame year? Did not the Moors come and dethrone that Effeminate King? You know the Story, and you may eaſily judge that the Devil, who ſince the Reign of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> diſpoſes not of Empires, could not be Author of that Oracle: And that it muſt certainly have been ſome great Cabaliſt, who learned it from one of the moſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Salamanders. For ſeeing the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamanders are great Lovers of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, they willingly acquaint us with the evils that are to befal the World for the want of that Vertue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But, Sir</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>do you think it a very chaeſte thing, and becoming Cabali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick Modeſty, to make uſe of that Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roclitous Organ by which they preached their Morality?</hi> Ah! for this once <hi>(ſaid the Count laughing)</hi> I perceive you have the Imagination diſtempered, and you
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151429:35"/> ſee not the Phyſical reaſon why the inflamed Salamander delights natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the moſt fiery hot places, and is attracted by...... <hi>I underſtand, I underſtand</hi> (ſaid I, interrupting him) <hi>you need not take the pains to explain your ſelf more fully.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Obſcurities of ſome Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles <hi>(continued he ſeriouſly)</hi> which you call Juggling and Cheating, is not Darkneſs the uſual Mantle of Truth? Does not God take pleaſure to hide himſelf under that Dusky Veil; and the Everlaſting Oracle which he hath left to his Children, I mean the Holy Scriptures; is it not wrapt up in an adorable Obſcurity; which confounds and miſleads the proud, as its light guids the humble?</p>
               <p>If that be all the ſcruple you have, my Son, I would not adviſe you to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay your entering into Commerce with the Elementary People. You will find them very honeſt folks, knowing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent, and Fearers of God. It i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e my Opinion, that you ſhould begi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the Salamanders; for in your Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure you have <hi>Mars</hi> in the Mid-hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151429:36"/> which imports that there is a great deal of Fire in all your actions. And as to Marriage, I would adviſe you to take a Sylphide; you'll live happier with her than with any of the others; for you have <hi>Jupiter</hi> on the Cuſp of your Aſcendant, within a Sextile of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> Now <hi>Jupiter</hi> rules over the Air and the People of the Air. However you muſt conſult your own heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the matter; for as you ſhall one day know, a Sage is governed by the internal Planets, and the Planets of the external Heavens ſerve only to make known to him more certainly the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of the Internal Heaven, which is in every Creature: So thar it lies at your Door now to tell me what your inclination is, to the end we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to your match with thoſe of the Elementary People whom you like beſt. <hi>Sir</hi> (anſwered I) <hi>that is an Affair, which in my opinion requires ſome little delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> I like you for that Anſwer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſaid he, clapping his hand upon my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſhoulder.)</hi> Conſult deliberately about that great matter, eſpecially with him who by Excellence is called, <hi>The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151429:36"/> of the Great Council.</hi> Go, betake your ſelf to Prayer, and to morrow about Two of the Clock after Noon, I will come and wait on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou.</p>
               <p>We returned towards <hi>Paris,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Road I put him again upon the Diſcourſe againſt Atheiſts and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines: I never heard more ſolid Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor better and more ſublime things ſaid for the Exiſtence of a God, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the blindneſs of thoſe who ſpend their lives without applying themſelves wholly to a ſerious and continual wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of him, from whom we have our being, and who does preſerve it. I wondred at the Character of the Man, and could not conceive, how at the ſame time he could be ſtrong and ſo weak; ſo admirable and ſo ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="conference">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:151429:37"/>
               <head>The Fourth Conference about Secret Sciences.</head>
               <p>I Stayed at home expecting the Count of <hi>Gabalis,</hi> as we had agreed at our parting. He came at the appointed hour, and accoſting me with a ſmiling air; Well, my Son <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> for which kind of the Inviſible People hath God given you the greateſt Inclination, and what Alliance will pleaſe you beſt, whether of the Salamanders, Gnomides, Nymphs or Sylphides? <hi>I am not as yet fully reſolved about that match, Sir,</hi> (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered I.) Who is in the fault then? <hi>(replied he.) To be free with you, Sir,</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>I cannot cure my imagination; it ſtill repreſents to me thoſe pretended Gueſts of the Elements as the Taſſels of Devils.</hi> O Lord! <hi>(cried he)</hi> O God of Light, diſperſe the darkneſs which ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and perverſe Education hath ſpread over the ſoul of this Elect; who, as you have made known to me, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtined by you to ſo great matters. And
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151429:37"/> you, my Son, ſhut not the Door a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Truth, which would come and lodge with you, be teachable. But it is all one, I care not whether you be or not; for indeed it is injurious to Truth, to prepare its wayes. It can break thorow Doors of Iron, and enter where it pleaſes, in ſpight of all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of Falſhood. What can you have to object againſt it? Hath not God, d'ye think created in the Elements ſuch Subſtances as I have deſcribed?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have not examined</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>if there be any poſſibility in the matter it ſelf; If one ſingle Element can furniſh Blood, Fleſh, and Bones? If there can be a Temperature without Mixture, and Actions without Contrariety? But granting that God could do it, what ſolid Argument is there that he hath done it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Will you be convinced of it preſently <hi>(replied he)</hi> without ſo much a-do? I'll go call the Sylphs of <hi>Cardan,</hi> you ſhall hear from their own mouths what they are, and what I have told you of them. <hi>No, not ſo, Sir, if you pleaſe</hi> (cried I briskly.) <hi>Wave, I adjure you, that kind of proof, until I be perſwaded that thoſe Blades
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151429:38"/> are no Enemies to God; for till then I'll die, ſooner than wrong my Conſcience by.....</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This, this is the ignorant and falſe pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of theſe unhappy Times <hi>(ſaid the Count in Choller, interrupting me)</hi> Why then is not the greateſt of Anchorites blotted out of the Calendar of Saints? And why are not his Statues burnt? It is a wrong that his venerable Aſhes are not raked up? And that they are not ſcattered in the Air, as the Aſhes of thoſe who are accuſed of having had Commerce with Devils? Did he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to exorciſe the Sylphs? And hath he not treated them as Men? What can you ſay to that now <hi>Seigneur Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſo,</hi> you and all your ſilly Doctors? Was the Sylph who diſcourſed to that Patriarch of his Nature, in your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion the Taſſel of a Devil; Did that incomparable Man conſult with a Gob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin about the Goſpel? And will you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him of having profaned the ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Myſteries, by diſcourſing of them with a Spright the Enemy of God? <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> and St. <hi>Jerome</hi> then very ill deſerve the great name that is given
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151429:38"/> them by the Learned; having wrote with ſo much eloquence the Elogy of a Man who was ſo courteous to Devils. If they took the Sylph for a Devil, they ought either to have ſtifled the Adventure, or interpreted in a ſpiritual Senſe that Sermon, or that ſo pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Apoſtrophie which the Anchorite, more credulous and zealous than you are, makes to the City of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria:</hi> And if they thought that Sylph a Creature participant, as he aſſures us, as well as we of Redemption; and if in their Opinion that Apparition was an extraordinary grace of God ſhew'd to the Saint, whoſe Life they wrote, are you reaſonable to pretend to more knowledge than <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and <hi>Jerome,</hi> and greater holineſs than Divine <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony?</hi> What would you have ſaid to that admirable man, had you been one of thoſe Ten thouſand Hermites, to whom he related the Converſation that he had with the Sylph? You, without doubt, wiſer and more inlightened than all thoſe Terreſtrial Angels, would have told the Saint, <hi>That his whole Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture was a meer Illuſion;</hi> and you
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151429:39"/> would have diſſwaded his Diſciple <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> from publiſhing to all the World a Story ſo inconſiſtent with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Philoſophy, and Common Senſe. Is it not true what I ſay?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is true</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>that I would have been of the Opinion, either to have ſaid nothing at all, or more of it. Athanaſius</hi> and St. <hi>Jerome (replied he)</hi> had no mind to ſpeak more of it; for they knew no more but that; and though they had known all, which could not be unleſs they were of our number; they would not have raſhly divulged the Secrets of Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>But why did not that Sylph (ſaid I) propoſe to St. <hi>Anthony,</hi> what you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to day to me? What <hi>(ſaid the Count laughing)</hi> Matrimony? Ha, ha, that had been to good purpoſe indeed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>It is true</hi> (replied I) <hi>that in all appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance the good Man would not have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the Match.</hi> No certainly <hi>(ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Count)</hi> for it would have been a tempting of God to have married a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that Age, and to have asked Children of him. <hi>How</hi> (replied I) <hi>do you marry with Sylphs then, to have Children by them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:151429:39"/> For what end elſe <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> are Men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver allowed to marry, for another end? <hi>I did not think</hi> (replied I) <hi>that ye expected or pretended to any Iſſue; but that all ye did, was onely to immortalize Sylphs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ha! You are in the wrong <hi>(continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he)</hi> the Charity of Philoſophers makes them propoſe for their end the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of the Sylphides: but Nature m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kes them deſirous to ſee them fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. You ſhall ſee, when you have a mind, thoſe Philoſophical Families in the Air. Happy were the World, if it had none but ſuch Families, and if there were no Children of Corruption in it. <hi>What do you call Children of Corruption, Sir?</hi> (ſaid I, interrupting him.)</p>
               <p>Such are <hi>(ſaid he)</hi> my Son, ſuch are all the Children who are born in the ordinary way; Children conceived by the Will of the Fleſh, not by the Will of God; Children of Wrath and Maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; in a word, Children of Men and Women. You have a mind to interrupt me; I know very well what you would ſay. Verily, my Son, you muſt know, that it was never the Will of the Lord
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151429:40"/> that Men and Women ſhould have Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by the way they procreate. The Deſign of the all-wiſe Creator was much more Noble; he intended the World ſhould have been peopled far o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than it is, if wretched <hi>Adam</hi> had not ſo groſly diſobeyed the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, Not to touch <hi>Eve;</hi> and if he had been ſatisfied with all the other Fruits of the Garden of Pleaſure, with the Beauty of the Nymphs and Sylphides; the World would not have had the diſgrace to be filled with Men, ſo imperfect; that they may paſs for Monſters, if compared with the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Philoſophers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How, Sir</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>by what I perceive, you believe that the crime of</hi> Adam <hi>is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe than the eating of the Apple?</hi> What, my Son <hi>(replied the Count)</hi> are you of the number of thoſe that have the ſimplicity to underſtand the Story of the Apple literally? Ha! You muſt know, that the Holy Tongue uſes thoſe innocent Metaphors, to keep us from conceiving Obſcene Notions of an Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which occaſioned all the Miſeries of Mankind. So, when <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaid, <hi>I will
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151429:40"/> aſcend the Palm tree, and gather the fruits thereof; he had another appetite than the eating, of Dates: that Tongue which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated by Angels, and uſed by them in ſinging Hymns to the Living God, hath no Terms to expreſs what it figuratively names, calling it an Apple or Date. But a Sage eaſily explains thoſe chaſte Figures, when he perceives that the Mouth or Taſte of</hi> Eve <hi>are not puniſhed, and that ſhe brings forth in pain: He knows that it is not the Taſte that was in the fault: And diſcovering what was the firſt ſin, by the care which the firſt ſinners had to cover ſome parts of their Bodies with Fig-tree Leaves, he concludes that it was not the will of God that Men ſhould multiply by that baſe way. O</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam! <hi>you ſhould have begotten none but men like your ſelf, or none but Heroes and Giants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pray now! what expedient was there,</hi> (ſaid I interrupting him) <hi>for one or other of thoſe mervellous Generations?</hi> To obey God <hi>(replied he)</hi> to touch none but Nymphs, Gnomes, Sylphides. or Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders. So none but Heroes would have ſprung from his Loins, and the Univerſe would have been peopled with
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151429:41"/> a wonderful Race; filled with ſtrength and wiſdom. God was pleaſed to let us gueſs at the difference that would have been betwixt that innocent world and the ſinful world which now we ſee, by ſuffering now and then Children to be begotten after the manner that he has projected. <hi>There has been ſometimes then Sir</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>ſome of thoſe Children of the Elements? And a Doctor of the</hi> Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne, <hi>who cited to me t'other day St.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, <hi>St.</hi> Jerome, <hi>and</hi> Gregory Nazian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zene, <hi>is miſtaken then, in believing that no fruit could ſpring from the loves of thoſe ſpirits for our women, or the commerce that men might have with certain Devils whom he called</hi> Hyphialtes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lactantius</hi> reaſoned better <hi>(replied the Count)</hi> and ſolid <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> hath learnedly decided, that thoſe copulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might not onely be fruitful; but that the Children ſo begotten, are of a far more generous and heroick nature than others. In effect, you ſhall read when you pleaſe the high feats of thoſe mighty and famous men, who as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſays, were begotten in that manner; we have amongſt us the Hiſtories of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151429:41"/> them in the Book of the Wars of the Lord, cited in the Twenty third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Numbers.</hi> However judge what a world it would be, if all its Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, for inſtance, reſembled <hi>Zoroa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>who is reputed to be the Author of Necromancy?</hi> The very ſame <hi>(ſaid the Count)</hi> of whom the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant have wrote that calumny, he had the honour to be the Son of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamander <hi>Oromaſis,</hi> and <hi>Vesta</hi> the Wife of <hi>Noah.</hi> He lived Twelve hundred years, the wiſeſt Monarch in the world, and then was by his Father <hi>Oro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſis</hi> tranſported into the Region of Salamanders. I make no doubt <hi>(ſaid I)</hi> but <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> is with the Salamander <hi>Oromaſis</hi> in the Region of Fire: but I would be loath to put ſuch an affront upon <hi>Noah,</hi> as you have done.</p>
               <p>The affront is not ſo great as you may imagine <hi>(replied the Count)</hi> all thoſe Patriarchs reckoned it a great honour to be the preſumptive Fathers of the Children, which the Sons of God were willing to beget upon their Wives; but this is likewiſe a little too ſtrong for you.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151429:42"/> Let us return to <hi>Oromaſis;</hi> he was belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of <hi>Veſta</hi> the Wife of <hi>Noah.</hi> That ſame <hi>Veſta</hi> after her death was the Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telary Genius of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Sacred Fire which ſhe would have carefully kept by Virgins, was to the honour of her Gallant the Salamander. Beſides <hi>Zoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſter,</hi> they had alſo a Daughter of an excellent Beauty and extream Wiſdom; ſhe was that Divine <hi>Egeria</hi> from whom <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> received all his Laws. She obliged <hi>Numa,</hi> whom ſhe loved, to build a Temple to her Mother <hi>Veſta,</hi> where the Sacred Fire was kept in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of her Father <hi>Oromaſis.</hi> This is the truth of the Fable which the Poets and Roman Hiſtorians have related of that Nymph <hi>Egeria. William Postoll,</hi> the leaſt ignorant of all who have ſtudied the Cabal in the Common Books, knew that <hi>Veſta</hi> was the Wife of <hi>Noah;</hi> but he was ignorant that <hi>Egeria</hi> was the Daughter of that <hi>Veſta;</hi> and not having read the ſecret Books of the Ancient Cabal, of which the Prince of <hi>Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula</hi> bought a Copy at ſo dear a rate; he believed that <hi>Egeria</hi> was only the good Genius of <hi>Noah</hi>'s Wife. We are
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151429:42"/> informed by theſe Books that <hi>Egeria</hi> was conceived upon the Water, when <hi>Noah</hi> wandered upon the avenging Floods that deluged the Univerſe. Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were then reduced to that little number which was ſaved in the Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtick Ark, which that ſecond Father of the World had built: This great Man groaning to ſee the dreadful puniſhment wherewith God chaſtiſed the Crimes occaſioned by the love that <hi>Adam</hi> had for his <hi>Eve;</hi> and perceiving that <hi>Adam</hi> had undone his poſterity, by preferring <hi>Eve</hi> to the Daughters of the Elements, and by denying her to Salamanders or Sylphs, who could eaſily have gained her love. <hi>Noah</hi> (I ſay) growing wiſe, by the fatal example of <hi>Adam,</hi> conſented that his Wife <hi>Veſta</hi> ſhould yield to the Salamander <hi>Oromaſis,</hi> the Prince of fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Subſtances; and likewiſe perſwaded his three Sons to give their three Wives to the Princes of the Three other Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The Univerſe by this means was in a ſhort time re-peopled with ſo heroick, knowing, beautiful, and rare Men, that their Poſterity dazzeled with their Vertues took them for Deities.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151429:43"/> One of the Sons of <hi>Noah</hi> rejects the counſel of his Father, and cannot reſiſt the Charms of his Wife, no more than <hi>Adam</hi> of his <hi>Eve:</hi> But as the Sin of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> blackned the ſouls of all his Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring, ſo the ſmall complaiſance, that <hi>Cham</hi> had for the Sylphs, marked all his black Poſterity. Hence comes (as our Cabaliſts ſay) the horrible colour of the Mores, and all thoſe hideous People who are commanded to inhabit the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Zone, as a Puniſhment of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Heat of their Father.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe are indeed pretty odd Records, Sir,</hi> (ſaid I, admiring the extravagancy of the Man) <hi>and your Cabal is of wonderful uſe for illuſtrating Antiquity.</hi> Wonderfully <hi>(replied he gravely)</hi> and without it Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Hiſtory, Fables, and Nature, are obſcure and unintelligible. For exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, you believe that the injury which <hi>Cham</hi> did to his Father, was ſuch as it appears by the Letter, verily it is a far different thing. <hi>Noah</hi> being come out of the Ark, and perceiving that his Wife <hi>Veſta</hi> grew fairer and fairer, by the commerce ſhe held with her Gallant <hi>Oro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſis,</hi> fell paſſionately in love with her
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151429:43"/> again. <hi>Cham</hi> fearing that his Father was about to people the Earth with a Race as black as his Mores, watched his opportunity one day, when the good old Man was full of Wine, and without mercy cut off his ſtones. You laugh?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I laugh</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>at the indiſcreet zeal of</hi> Cham. You ſhould rather admire <hi>(re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Count)</hi> the Civility of the Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander <hi>Oromaſis,</hi> whom Jealouſie hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred not to pity his Rivals Misfortune; he taught his ſon <hi>Zoroaſter,</hi> otherways called <hi>Japhet,</hi> the name of the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent God, which expreſſeth his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal fecundity: <hi>Japhet,</hi> with his Brother <hi>Shem,</hi> marching backwards towards the Patriarch, pronounced ſix times by turns the dreadful Name of JABAMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AH, and made the old Man whole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. This Hiſtory, ill underſtood, made the Greeks ſay that the ancienteſt of the Gods was gelt by one of his Sons: but the truth of the matter is as I have told you. From whence you may conclude that the morality of the people of the Fire is far more courteous than ours, yea even than of the people of the Air or Water; for the Jealouſie of theſe is
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151429:44"/> Cruel, as Divine <hi>Paracelſus</hi> informs us in an adventure which he relates, and which was ſeen by all the Town of <hi>Stauffembergh.</hi> A Philoſopher, with whom a Nymph engaged in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of Immortality, was ſo diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt as to fall in love with a VVoman; as he was at Dinner with his new Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſs and ſome Friends, they ſaw in the Air one of the lovlieſt Thighs and Legs that could be imagined: The Inviſible Lover was willing to ſhew it to the Friends of her Diſloyal Servant, to the end they might judge how much he was in the wrong, to prefer a VVoman to her. After which, the inraged Nymph killed him on the ſpot.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ha, ha! Sir</hi> (cried I) <hi>that is enough to put me out of conceit with ſuch Miſſes.</hi> I confeſs <hi>(replied he)</hi> their nicety is a little too violent; but if amongſt our VVomen, ſome provoked Miſſes have been known to diſpatch their perjured Gallants, it is not to be wondred at if thoſe ſo beautiful and faithful Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearts, be inraged when they find themſelves betrayed; and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they exact no more from Men, but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151429:44"/> that they would abſtain from VVomen, whoſe defects they cannot away with; and that they allow us to make love to as many of themſelves as we pleaſe. They prefer the Intereſt and Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their Companions to their private fatisfaction; and are glad when the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges beſtow upon their Republick as many Children as they are able to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But in fine, Sir</hi> (replied I) <hi>how comes it to paſs that there are ſo few inſtances of what you tell me?</hi> There are a great many, Child <hi>(continued he)</hi> but Men reflect not on them, or believe them not; or in a word explain them amiſs, for want of the knowledge of our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. They aſcribe to Devils, all that ſhould be attributed to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Elements. A little Gnome procures the love of the famous <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene</hi> of the Croſs, Abbeſs of a Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery at <hi>Cordova</hi> in <hi>Spain;</hi> at twelve years of age ſhe began to render him happy, and they continued their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce for the ſpace of Thirty years. An ignorant Confeſſor perſwades <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene</hi> that her Gallant was a Goblin,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151429:45"/> and obliges her to beg Abſolution from Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Third. Nevertheleſs it is impoſſible that it could be a Devil; for all <hi>Europe</hi> knows, and <hi>Caſſiodorus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> hath left on Record to Poſterity, the Miracle that was daily done in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of that Holy Nun, which in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance would not have happened, if her commerce with the Gnome had been ſo devilliſh as the Venerable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor imagined. That Doctor, if I miſtake not, would have boldly affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Sylph who immortalized himſelf with the young <hi>Gertrude,</hi> a Nun of the Monaſtery of <hi>Nazareth</hi> in the Dioceſs of <hi>Cologne,</hi> was ſome De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. <hi>Without doubt</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>and I think ſo too.</hi> Ha! my Son <hi>(continued he laughing)</hi> the Devil is not unhappy then, in that he could entertain a Commerce of Gallantry with a Girl of Thirteen years of Age, and write to her the ſweet Love-letters that were found in her Cabinet.</p>
               <p>Believe, my Child, believe, that in the Region of Death the Devil hath ſadder Imployments and more conform to the hatred which the God of Purity
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151429:45"/> purſues him with: but thus men wilfully ſhut their eyes. We find, for inſtance in <hi>Titus Livius,</hi> that <hi>Romulus</hi> was the Son of <hi>Mars;</hi> the Wits ſay, that it is a Fable: the Divines, that he was the Son of a Devil: the Drolls, that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>Sylvia</hi> loſt her Gloves, and that ſhe would cover the ſhame of it, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they were ſtollen from her by a God. We who know Nature, and who are called by God from that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his mervellous light; we know, that that ſame pretended <hi>Mars</hi> was a Salamander, who taken with the young <hi>Sylvia,</hi> made her the Mother of great <hi>Romulus,</hi> the Hero, who having found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his ſtately City, was by his Father carried away in a Flaming Chariot, as <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> was by <hi>Oromaſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Salamander was the Father of <hi>Servius Paulus; Titus Livius</hi> ſays it was the God of Fire, deceived by the reſemblance; and the ignorant have paſt the ſame Judgment on him as on the Father of <hi>Romulus.</hi> The famous <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules,</hi> and the invincible <hi>Alexander,</hi> were the Sons of the greateſt of the Sylphs. The Hiſtorians, ignorant of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151429:46"/> that, have ſaid that <hi>Jup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter</hi> was their Father. They ſaid true, for as you have been told, thoſe Sylphs, Nymphs, and Salamanders, being reckoned Deities, the Hiſtorians, who believed them to be ſo, called all that were begotten by them the Children of Gods.</p>
               <p>Such were the Divine <hi>Plato,</hi> the more Divine <hi>Apollonius Thianeus, Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules, Achilles, Sarpedon, Pius Aeneas,</hi> and renowned <hi>Melchiſedeck;</hi> for do you know who was <hi>Melchiſedecks</hi> Father? <hi>No really Sir</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>for St.</hi> Paul <hi>knew it not.</hi> Nay ſay, that he would not tell <hi>(replied the Count)</hi> and that he was not permitted to reveal the Cabaliſtick My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; he well knew that the Father of <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> was a Sylph, and that that King of <hi>Salem</hi> was conceived in the Ark by the wife of <hi>Shem.</hi> The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of that High-Prieſts ſacrifiſing, was the ſame, which his Couſin <hi>Egeria</hi> taught King <hi>Numa,</hi> as well as the ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a Supream Deity without I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and Statue: by reaſon whereof the Romans ſometime after falling into Idolatry, burnt the Holy Books of <hi>Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> which were dictated by <hi>Egeria.</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:151429:46"/> The firſt God of the Romans was the true God, they had true Sacrifice, they offered Bread and Wine to the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Maſter of the World; but that was wholly perverted in ſucceeding Times; yet God, in acknowledgment of that Primitive Worſhip, gave that City, which had owned his Sovereignty, the Empire of the Univerſe. The ſame Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice which <hi>Melchiſedeck........</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I beg of you, Sir</hi> (ſaid I, interrupting him) <hi>let us wave</hi> Melchiſedeck, <hi>the</hi> Sylph <hi>that begot him, his Couſin</hi> Egeria, <hi>and the Sacrifice of Bread and Wine. Theſe Arguments ſeem to me a little remote; and you would much oblige me, to tell me news of a freſher date; for I heard a Doctor ſay, who was asked what was become of that Satyre who appeared to St.</hi> Anthony, <hi>and whom you have called a Sylph; that all thoſe Blades are dead now. And indeed it may very well be, ſince you acknowledge them to be mortal; and that we hear no news of them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I pray God <hi>(replied the Count in a little heat)</hi> I pray God, who knows all things, that he would never know that unknowing man, who ſo ſottiſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151429:47"/> what he knows not. Confound him and all ſuch Coxcombs. Which way hath he learnt that the Elements are deſert, and that all thoſe mervellous people are annihilated? If he would have taken the pains to read a little Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, and not like good Women, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to the Devil what-ever tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcends the Chimerical Theory which he hath framed to himſelf of Nature, he would have found in all Times and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſufficient inſtances of what I have now told you.</p>
               <p>What would your Doctor ſay to that Authentick Story which happened lately in <hi>Spain?</hi> A lovely Sylphide was belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of a Spaniard, lived with him three years, had three fine Children to him, and then died. Will one ſay that it was a She-Devil? A learned An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer indeed! by what Philoſophy can the Devil form to himſelf the Body of a Woman, conceive, bring forth, and give ſuck? What proof is there in Scripture of that extravagant Power, which on this occaſion your Divines are obliged to grant to the Devil? And what probable Reaſon can their weak
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151429:47"/> Phyſicks furniſh them with. The Jeſuit <hi>Delrio,</hi> a Man of Sincerity and Candor, faithfully relates ſeveral ſuch Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and without perplexing himſelf with Phyſical Reaſons, ſlips his Neck out of the Collar, by ſaying, That thoſe Sylphides were Devils: So true it is, That your greateſt Doctors know no more moſt times than ſilly Women! So true it is, That God loves to retire into his Cloudy Throne, and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſing the Darkneſs which incompaſſes his dreadful Majeſty, he diſcovers not his Verities, but to ſuch as are of an humble heart. Learn from the Sages to give the Devils no power in Nature, ſince the fatal Stone hath ſhut them up in the Bottomleſs Pit. Learn of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers alwayes to ſearch for Natural Cauſes in all extraordinary Emergents; and when Natural Cauſes fail, make your recourſe to God and his holy Angels, but never to the Devils, who do no more but ſuffer: otherwiſe you will many times blaſpheme before you are aware; and attribute to the Devil the moſt mervellous VVorks of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:151429:48"/>
               <p>For Example, VVhen you are told that the Divine <hi>Apollonius Thianeus</hi> was conceived without the help of any Man, and that one of the higheſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamanders deſcended to immortalize himſelf with his Mother; you'll ſay that that Salamander was a Devil, and you'll give the Devil the glory of the generation of one of the greateſt Men that ever ſprung from our Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Marriage-Beds.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But, Sir</hi> (ſaid I, interrupting him) <hi>that ſame</hi> Apollonius <hi>is amongſt us repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to have been a great Sorcerer, and that is all the good that is ſaid of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is <hi>(replied the Count)</hi> one of the ſtrangeſt effects of Ignorance and perverſe Education; becauſe one has heard his Nurſe tell Tales of Sorcerers, what-ever comes to paſs extraordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, muſt have the Devil for Author. It is in vain for the greateſt Doctors to talk, we will never believe them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they ſay as our Nurſes ſay. <hi>Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> is not begotten of a Man, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the Language of Birds, he is ſeen the ſame day in ſeveral places of the VVorld, he diſappears before the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151429:48"/> Emperor <hi>Domitian,</hi> who would have uſed him ill: He raiſes a Maid by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Onomancy: He ſays at <hi>Epheſus</hi> in an Aſſembly of all <hi>Aſia,</hi> that at the very inſtant the Tyrant is killed at <hi>Rome.</hi> That Man is to be tried, the Nurſe ſays he is a Sorcerer; St. <hi>Jerome</hi> and St. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> Martyr, ſay he was only a great Philoſopher. <hi>Jerome, Juſtin,</hi> and we Cabaliſts, ſhall be Enthuſiaſts, and the little VVoman ſhall carry the day. Ha! Let the Ignorants periſh in their Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances; but for you, my Son, ſave your ſelf from the Shipwrack.</p>
               <p>VVhen you read that the Famous <hi>Merlin</hi> was born without the help of Man of a Nun, the Daughter of a King of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> and that he fore-told things future more clearly than <hi>Tyreſia.</hi> Say not with the Vulgar, <hi>That he was the Son of an</hi> Incubus, ſeeing there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was any; nor, <hi>That he propheſied by the Black Art,</hi> ſeeing the Devil is the moſt ignorant of all Creatures; accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the holy <hi>Cabal.</hi> Say with the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, <hi>That the Britiſh Princeſs was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in her Solitude by a Sylph, who took pity on her; that he made it his buſineſs to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151429:49"/> divert her: that he knew how to pleaſe her, and that their Son</hi> Merlin <hi>was bred by the Sylph in all Sciences, and learned of him to do all the Mervels which are rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Hiſtories of</hi> England.</p>
               <p>Neither offer that Affront to the Counts of <hi>Cleves,</hi> to ſay, <hi>That the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is their Fore-father,</hi> and entertain a better opinion of the Sylph, who as Hiſtory tells us, came to <hi>Cleves</hi> in a miraculous Ship drawn by a Swan, that was yoked to it with a Silver Chain. That Sylph having begot many Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren upon the Heireſs of <hi>Cleves,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted one day at Noon in his Aereal Ship, in the ſight of all the people. Now what hurt hath he done your Doctors, that they ſet him up for a Devil?</p>
               <p>But will you have ſo little regard to the honour of the Houſe of <hi>Luſignan?</hi> and will you give your Counts of <hi>Poiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> a Diabolical Extraction? VVhat will you ſay of their famous Mother? <hi>I believe Sir</hi> (ſaid I interrupting him) <hi>you are about to tell me Tales of</hi> Melu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſina. Ha! <hi>(replied he)</hi> if you deny me the Hiſtory of <hi>Meluſina,</hi> I give you over for loſt: but if you deny it, we muſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151429:49"/> burn the Books of great <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n five or ſix different places maintains that <hi>Meluſina</hi> was a Nymph; and you muſt give the lie to your Hiſtorians, who ſay that ſince her death, or rather ſince ſhe vaniſhed out of her Husbands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight, ſhe hath never failed (whenſoever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her Off-ſpring were threatned with any misfortune, or any King of <hi>France</hi> was to die by an extraordinary death) to appear in Mourning upon the great Tower of the Caſtle of <hi>Luſignan</hi> which ſhe built. You would have a quarrel with all that are deſcended from that Nymph, or that are allied to that Houſe, if you ſhould obſtinately maintain it was the Devil.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do ye think, Sir</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>that theſe Lords like beſt to be deſcended from Sylphs?</hi> They would without doubt like it beſt <hi>(repl ed he)</hi> if they knew what I tell you, and they would reckon thoſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary procreations to be a great honour. They would know, if they had a glimpſe of the Cabal, that that kind of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation being more ſuitable to the way that God in the beginning intended men ſhould be multiplied; the Children that
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151429:50"/> ſpring from it are happier, more valiant, wiſe, renowned, and more bleſſed of God. Is it not more glorious for thoſe illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Men to be deſcended from ſo perfect, wiſe, and powerful Creatures, than from ſome naſty Goblin, or infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Aſmodeus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>our Divines are far from ſaying that the Devil is the Father of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thoſe who come into the World, when it is not known who begot them. They ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Devil to be a Spirit, and that ſo he cannot generate. Gregory o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Nice</hi> (replied the Count) ſays not ſo, for he holds that the Devils multipli'd among themſelves, as Men do. <hi>We are not of his Opinion</hi> (anſwered I) <hi>but it comes to paſs (ſay our Doctors.....)</hi> Ha! ſay not (ſaid the Count interrupting me,) ſay not, what they ſay, elſe you'l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeak as they do, a very foul and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcene impertinency. What abominable ſhift have they found there? It is ſtrang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how they have all unanimouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced that Pollution, and placed lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Goblins in ambuſcado, to make ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the idle Brutality of ſolitary Perſons, and thereby to hatch thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:151429:50"/> miraculous Men, whoſe illuſtrious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory they ſtain by ſo baſe a Conception. <hi>Do they call that to play the Philoſophers? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s it beſeeming the Majeſty of God, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay that he does ſo far comply with the Devil, as to favour ſuch abominations, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rant them the Bleſſing of Fruitfulneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich he hath denied to Saints, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ward thoſe Impurities by ereating for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ch embryo's of Iniquity, more Heroick Souls, than for thoſe who have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tten in the Chaſtity of a lawful Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>age? Is it be-fitting Religion, to ſay as our Doctors do, that the Devil by that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eteſtable Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ifice can make a Maid with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hild in her ſleep without hurting her Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nity; which is as abſurd as the Story that</hi> Thomas Aquinas <hi>(other-ways a very ſolid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uthor, and who underſtood a little of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abal) forgot himſelf ſo far, as to relate his ſixth</hi> Quodlibet, <hi>of a Maid lying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith her Father, to whom he makes the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne accident happen, that befell the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aughter of</hi> Jeremiah (<hi>as ſome heretical</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abins ſay) <hi>who make her to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ived the great Cabaliſt</hi> Ben Syrah, <hi>by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tring into the Bath after the Prophet, are ſwear that that impertinency hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n invented by ſome.....</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:151429:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>If I durst interrupt your Declamation, Sir,</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>I would confeſs that it were to be wiſhed that our Doctors had ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined ſome Solution, which might not have been ſo offenſive to chaſte Ears, ſuch as yours; or elſe they ſhould have abſolutely denied the inſtances on which the question is grounded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An excellent expedient (<hi>replied the Count</hi>) fie, fie! to deny evident truths: put your ſelf in the place of a Doctor with a Hood) and ſuppoſe that the bleſſed <hi>Danhuzerus</hi> came to you as to the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of his Religion....</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As he was ſaying ſo, a Lackey came to acquaint me that a Young Lord was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſee me.</hi> I will not be ſeen by him <hi>(ſaid the Count) I beg your Pardon Sir</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>you well perceive by that Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Name that I cannot deny my ſelf: take the pains then to go into that Cloſet.</hi> Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is needleſs (<hi>ſaid he</hi>) I'll go make m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſelf inviſible. <hi>Ha! Sir</hi> (cried I) <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Devilry (if you pleaſe) I like not jeſting with ſuch edged Tools.</hi> Strange Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance (<hi>ſaid the Count laughing and ſhrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> up his Shoulders</hi>) not to know tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o become inviſible, there is no more
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151429:51"/> requiſite but to put the contrary of the Light before ones ſelf. <hi>With that he went into the Cloſet) and at the ſame time the Young Lord came into my Chamber: I beg his pardon if I talked not to him of my Adventure.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="conference">
               <head>The Fifth Conference about Secret Sciences.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe great Lord being gone, as I came back from waiting on him out, I found the Count of</hi> Gabalis <hi>in my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> It is great pity (<hi>ſaid he</hi>) that the lofty Lord who has juſt now been gone, ſhall one day be one of the 72 Princes of the <hi>Sanhedrin</hi> of the New Law; for were it not for that, he would prove a great Subject for the Secret Cabal; he is a Man of a deep reach, a clear, vaſt, ſublime, and daring Wit; there is the figure of <hi>Geomancy</hi> that I caſt for him while ye were in Diſcourſe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I never ſaw more happy points,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151429:52"/> and which denoted ſo noble a Soul; look to that<note n="(a)" place="margin">Terms of Geomancy,</note> Mother, what magnanimity ſhe gives him. That<note n="(b)" place="margin">Terms of Geomancy,</note> Daughter, ſhall procure him the Purple. I am vexed at her, and Fortune too, becauſe they deprive Philoſophy of a Subject that perhaps might ſurpaſs you. But where were we when he came?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You talked to me, Sir,</hi> (replied I) <hi>of a Saint that I never ſaw in the Roman Calender, I think you called him</hi> Danhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerus: Ha! I remember (<hi>anſwered he</hi>) I bid you put your ſelf in the place of one of your Doctors, and ſuppoſe that the bleſſed <hi>Danhuzerus</hi> came to open his Conſcience to you, and told you.</p>
               <p>Sir, the fame of your knowledge hath brought me hither from beyond the <hi>Alpes;</hi> I have a little ſcruple that pinches me. In a Mountain of <hi>Italy</hi> there is a Nymph keeps her Court; a thouſand Nymphs as lovely almoſt as her ſelf, wait upon her. Many hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, learned, and civil Gentlemen, come thither from all parts of the habitable World; they love thoſe
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151429:52"/> Nymphs, and are beloved of them; there they lead the ſweeteſt life imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; they beget moſt lovely Children on thoſe whom they love; they adore the Living God, they wrong no Body, and they hope for immortality. As I was one day walking upon that Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, I pleaſed the Nymph Queen, ſhe made her ſelf viſible, and ſhew'd me her charming Court. The <hi>Sages</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that ſhe loved me, reſpected me almoſt as their Prince; they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted me to yield to the Sighs and Beauty of the Nymph; ſhe her ſelf told me her Sufferings, and omitted nothing that might affect my Heart; and at length told me, that ſhe muſt die if I would not love her: and that if I loved her, ſhe would be indebted to me for her Immortality. The Reaſonings of thoſe Learned Men convinced my mind, and the charms of the Nymph won my heart; I love her, and have very hopeful Children by her; but in the midſt of my Felicity, I am ſometimes troubled by calling to mind that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> perhaps approves not too well of this. I came to you, Sir, to conſult,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151429:53"/> what that Nymph is, thoſe Sages and Children, and in what ſtate my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is? There! Maſter Doctor what Anſwer would you make to Lord <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huzerus?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I would tell him</hi> (anſwered I) <hi>with all the reſpect that I owe you,</hi> Seigneur Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huzerus <hi>you are a little phanatical; or elſe your Viſion is an Inchantment; your Children and Miſtriſs are Hobgoblins; your Sages are Fools, and your Conſcience is ſeared.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With that anſwer (<hi>my Son</hi>) you may deſerve a Doctors Hood, but you'll never merit to be re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>d amongſt us <hi>(replied the Count fetching a deep ſigh)</hi> there is the barbarous Diſpoſition of all the Doctors now a days. A poor Sylph dares not ſhew himſelf but he is imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately taken for a Goblin; a Nymph muſt not endeavour Immortality un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſhe paſs for an impure Apparition; and a Salamander dares not appear for fear of being taken for a Devil, and the pure Flamet whereof he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, for the Fire of Hell that never leaves him. It is to much purpoſe for them, that they may diſpel thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious ſuſpitions, to make the ſign of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151429:53"/> the Croſs when they appear, bow the Knee at the Divine Names, yea, and pronounce them with reverence. Theſe are vain cautions, they cannot obtain that Men would not repute them the Enemies of God, whom they more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly adore than they that flee from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In earneſt, Sir,</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Sylphs to be very devote?</hi> Moſt devote <hi>(anſwered he</hi>) and moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for a Deity. The excellent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes they make us upon the Divine Eſſence, and their admirable Prayers edifie us exceedingly. <hi>Have they Prayers alſo</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>I would willingly have one of them?</hi> It is eaſie to ſatisfie you <hi>(re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied he)</hi> and to the end I may not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late one that may be ſuſpected, or that you may imagine fra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d by my ſelf; liſten to that which the <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> who gave reſponſes in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Delphos,</hi> taught the <hi>Pagans,</hi> and is related by <hi>Porphyrius;</hi> it contains ſublime Theology; and by it you'll ſee that it was no fault of thoſe wiſe Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, if the World adored not the true God.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
                  <body>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:151429:54"/>
                     <head>The Prayer of the <hi>Salamaders.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IMmortal, Eternal, Ineffable and Holy Father of all Things, who inceſſantly art carried on the rolling chariot of ever-turning Worlds. Ruler of the Etherian Fields, where the Throne of thy Power is raiſed; from the height whereof thy dreadful Eyes diſcover all, and thy Holy and Bleſſed Ears hear every thing. Hear thy Children whom thou haſt loved from the beginning of Ages; for thy Bright, thy Great and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Majeſty ſhines over the World, and the Starry Heavens. O ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Fire, thou art elevated above them; there thou inlightens and entertains thy ſelf by thy own Brightneſs, and from thy being
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151429:54"/> flow out continual ſtreams of Light which nouriſh thine infinite Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. That infinite Spirit produces all things, and makes that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhauſtible Treaſure of Matter, which cannot be wanting to the Generation that always inviron it by reaſon of the innumerable Forms wherewith it is impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, and with which thou filled'ſt it in the beginning. From that Spirit ſpring alſo thoſe moſt Holy Kings who ſtand about thy Throne, and make up thy Court. O univerſal and onely Father! O Father of the bleſſed Mortals and Immortals, thou haſt in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar created Powers, who are won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully like to thy Eternal Thought, and thine Adorable Eſſence. Thou haſt placed them above the Angels, the Meſſengers of thy Will in the World. In fine thou haſt created us a third kind of Soveraigns in the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151429:55"/> Elements: Our continual Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe is to praiſe thee, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore thy Will and Pleaſure. We are inflamed with a deſire of poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing thee. O Father, O Mother, the tendereſt of Mothers! O won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Example of the Feelings and Tenderneſs of Mothers! O Son, the Flower of all Sons! O Form of all Forms! Soul, Spirit, Harmony and Number of all Things.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>What ſay ye now to that Prayer of the <hi>Salamanders? Is it not very Learned, very Sublime and very Devote? And beſides very Obſcure too</hi> (anſwered I) <hi>I heard a Preacher paraphraſe upon it, who from thence proved that the Devil amongſt his other Vices, is a notorious great Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite.</hi> Ho! (<hi>cried the Count</hi>) what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy have ye then poor Elementary People? ye ſpeak aſtoniſhingly of the nature of God, the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, of aſſiſtent intelligences, of the Angels and Heavens. Ye make admirable Prayers, and teach them to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151429:55"/> Men; and when all is done, ye are but hypocritical Goblins!</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir</hi> (ſaid I interrupting him) <hi>I like not at all the Apoſtrophies you uſe to thoſe People.</hi> Well, well, my Son (<hi>replied he</hi>) be not afraid that I call them: but let not your weakneſs ſo far work upon you at leaſt, as for the future to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that you ſee not ſo many inſtances as you would of their Alliance with Men. Alas! Where is that Woman whoſe imagination your Doctors have not ſpoiled, who reflects not on that commerce with Horrour, and who would not quake at the aſpect of a <hi>Sylph?</hi> Where is the Man that flies not from the ſight of them, if he incline a little to be good? Do we but very ſeldom find an Honeſt Man that deſires their Familiarity? And do any but the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched, Covetous, Ambitious and Cheats, covet that Honour, which they ſhall never have though <hi>(VIVE DIE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>)</hi> becauſe the fear of the Lord is the beginning of Wiſdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What becomes then</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>of all thoſe People volant; ſeeing Honeſt Men are now ſo prejudiced againſt them?</hi> Ho! the Arm
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151429:56"/> of God (<hi>ſaid he</hi>) is not ſhortned, and the Devil reaps not all the profit which he hoped from the Ignorance and Error that he hath ſpread abroad to their prejudice; for beſides that the Philoſophers, who are numerous, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy it as much as they can, by whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly renouncing Women: God has per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted theſe People to uſe all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Arts they can deviſe for conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with Men without their knowledge. <hi>What d'ye tell me, Sir</hi> (cried I) I tell you the truth (<hi>continued he</hi>) Do you believe that a Dog can have Children by a Woman? <hi>No</hi> (anſwered I) And an Ape (added he?) <hi>Neither</hi> (replied I.) And a Bear <hi>(continued he?) Neither Dog, Bear, nor Ape,</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt impoſſible; it is contrary to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Reaſon, and Common Senſe.</hi> Good (<hi>ſaid the Count</hi>) but are not the Kings of the <hi>Goths</hi> ſprung from a Bear and a Swediſh Princeſs? Hiſtory ſays ſo. <hi>It is true</hi> (replied I) And the Peguſians and Syonians of the <hi>Indies (anſwered he)</hi> are they not begotten by a Dog upon a Woman? <hi>I have heard that alſo</hi> (ſaid I.) And that Portugueſe Woman <hi>(con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151429:56"/> he)</hi> who being expoſed on a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert Iſland, had Children by a great Baboon? <hi>Our Divines</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>anſwer to that Sir) that the Devil putting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the ſhape of thoſe Beaſts....</hi> You are again about to alledge to me <hi>(ſaid the Count interrupting me)</hi> the ſordid imaginations of your Authors. Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand then once for all, that the Sylphs perceiving that they are taken for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils when they appear in Humane ſhape, that they may leſſen the Averſion which People have to them; take the ſhape of thoſe Animals, and ſo accommodate themſelves to the whimſical weakneſs of Women, who would have a lovely Sylph in Horrour, and are not ſtartled at a Dog or Monkey. I could tell you many little ſtories of the Ladies Lap-dogs, with ſome Virgins in the World; but that I have a greater Secret to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to you.</p>
               <p>Know (my Son) that ſuch an one believes himſelf to be the Son of a Man, who is the Son of a Sylph. Such a Man thinks he is with his Wife, who una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares is immortaliſing a Nymph. A Wife thinks ſhe has her Husband in her
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151429:57"/> Arms, who is imbracing a Salamander; and ſuch a Maid would ſwear when ſhe awakes that ſhe is a Virgin, who in her ſleep hath had the honour ſhe dreamt not of. So the Devil and the Ignorant are equally abuſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How!</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>could not the Devil by awaking that ſleeping Maid hinder the</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamander <hi>from becoming immortal?</hi> He could <hi>(replied the Count)</hi> if the Sages took not a care of that; but we teach all thoſe People the way of binding the Devils, and of oppoſing their Attempts. Did I not tell you t'other day that the <hi>Sylphs</hi> and other Elementary Lords are too happy that we are pleaſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct them in the Cabal. Were it not for us the Devil their great Enemy would exceedingly diſturb them, and they would find it hard to immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize themſelves without the privacy of Maids.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I cannot ſufficiently admire</hi> (replied I) <hi>the profound ignorance, wherein we live; we believe that the Powers of the Air help the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>morous ſometimes to the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their deſires. The matter is quite otherways then; for the powers of the Air
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151429:57"/> want the aſſiſtance of Men in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their loves.</hi> You have hit it, my Son <hi>(continued the Count)</hi> the Sage brings ſuccour to thoſe poor people, who without him are too wretched and weak to reſiſt the Devil; but truly when a Sylph hath learnt from us Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baliſtically to pronounce the powerful name <hi>NEHMAHMIAH,</hi> and to joyn it in form with the delicious name <hi>ELIAEL;</hi> all the powers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs betake them to their Heels, and the Sylphs peaceable injoys the beloved Object.</p>
               <p>Thus was immortalized the ingenious Sylph, who took the ſhape of the Lover of a Young Lady of <hi>Seville;</hi> its a known Hiſtory. The Young Spaniſh Lady was Beautiful, but as cruel as fair. A Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> who loved her in vain, reſolved one morning to be gone without taking leave, and to travel until he were cured of his fruitleſs paſſion. A Sylph finding the fair one to his mind, thought it beſt to nick the time, and arming himſelf with the Directions that he had from one of us, to defend himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Croſſes, that the Devil, envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151429:58"/> of his happineſs might raiſe to him; he goes and viſits the Lady under the diſguiſe of the abſent Lover; he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, he ſighs, and is rejected. He urges, ſolicites, and perſeveres: After ſome months he wins upon her, gains her Love, perſwades her, and at length is made happy. Their Amours are fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful by a Son, who was ſecretly born without the knowledge of the Parents, being concealed by the skill of the Aere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Gallant. Their Love continues and is bleſſed with a ſecond Conception. In the mean time the Gentleman cured by abſence, returns to <hi>Seville,</hi> and being impatient to ſee his cruel Miſtriſs, goes with all ſpeed to tell her, that now at length he is in a condition not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe her; and that he is come to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint her that he loves her no more.</p>
               <p>Imagine but with your ſelf the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Young Lady, her An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, her Tears, Reproaches, and all their ſurpriſing Conference. She main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains that ſhe hath yielded to his will; he denies it; that their Child is in ſuch a place, that he is the Father of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in her Womb; he obſtinately diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owns
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151429:58"/> all. She is comfortleſs, tears her Hair; the Parents come running at her cries; the deſperate Lover perſiſts in her Complaints, and invectives; it is proved that the Gentleman was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for two years; they ſearch for the firſt Child and find it, and the ſecond was born at the time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what part acted the Aereal Gallant</hi> (ſaid I interrupting him) <hi>all this while?</hi> I well perceive <hi>(anſwered the Count)</hi> that you think, he did ill in abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Miſtriſs to the rigour of her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, or the fury of the Inquiſition: bu he had reaſon to complain of her, ſhe was not devote enough; for when theſe Gentlemen immortalize them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they labour ſeriouſly, and live with much ſanctity, that they may not loſe the right that they have acquired to the chief good. And ſo they will have the perſon to whom they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied, lead an exemplary Life; as is to be ſeen in the famous Adventure of a Young Lord of <hi>Bavaria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was over-whelmed with grief for the loſs of his Wife whom he paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately loved. A Sylphide was adviſed by
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151429:59"/> one of our Sages to take the ſhape of that Woman; ſhe took his Counſel, and went and preſented her ſelf to the young Mourner, ſaying, that God had raiſed her again to comfort him in his extream affliction. They lived many years together, and had very lovely Children; but this young Lord was not ſo good a man as to retain the wiſe Sylphide, he ſwore and talked Baudy. She often admoniſhed him; but finding that her Admonitions were in vain, one day ſhe evaniſhed, leaving him onely her Coats, and ſorrow that he had not followed her holy Counſels. So that you ſee, my Son, that the Sylphs have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſometimes to diſappear; and you perceive that the Devil cannot hinder, no more than the Capricious Whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of your Divines, but that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Elements ſucceſsfully endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their immortality when they are aſſiſted by ſome one or other of our Sages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But really and in good truth, Sir</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied I) <hi>are you perſwaded that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is ſo great an Enemy to thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchers of Young Maids?</hi> A mortal Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151429:59"/> 
                  <hi>(ſaid the Count)</hi> and eſpecially to the Nymphs, Sylphs, and Salamanders. For as for the Gnomes, he does not hate them ſo much, for, as I think I told you, theſe Gnomes terrified at the houling of the Devils which they hear in the Center of the Earth, chuſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to continue mortal than to run the risk of being ſo tormented, if they acquired immortality. Hence it is that the Gnomes have pretty good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with their Neighbours the Devils. Theſe perſwade the Gnomes, naturally very kind to men, that it is great ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice done to men, and a deliverance from a great danger, to oblige them to renounce their immortality; for that end they ingage to furniſh him, whom they can perſwade to that renunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with as much money as he ſhall pleaſe to ask, to avert the dangers that may threaten his Life during a certain ſpace of time, or what other condition; whicn he who makes that accurſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact ſhall pleaſe: ſo the Devil, wicked Rogue as he is, by the meditaion of that Gnome, makes the Soul of that Man become mortal, and deprives it of a right to Life eternal.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:151429:60"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>How, Sir</hi> (cried I) <hi>are not theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacts whereof Demonographers relate ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny examples, in your opinion then, made with the Devil?</hi> No ſure <hi>(replied the Count)</hi> hath not the Prince of the World been caſt out? Is not he ſhut up? Is not he bound? Is he not the <hi>Caput Mortuum,</hi> and <hi>terra damnata,</hi> which hath ſunk to the bottom of the operation of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream and Architypical Stagyriſt? Can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e aſcend unto the Region of Light, and ſpread his concentrated darkneſs there? He can do nothing againſt Man. He can onely inſpire into the Gnomes his Neighbours, to come and make ſuch Propoſitions to thoſe whom he fears moſt will be ſaved; to the end their Soul may die with their Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>According to your Doctrine then</hi> (added I) <hi>theſe Souls die?</hi> They die, Child (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered he) becauſe their Soul dies with the Body. <hi>They come off on very eaſie terms then</hi> (replied I) <hi>and are very lightly puniſhed for ſo enormous a Crime as the renouncing of their Baptiſm, and the death of their Saviour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Call you that <hi>(ſaid the Count)</hi> a ſlight puniſhment to enter into the dark Abyſs
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151429:60"/> of Nothing? Know that this is a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er puniſhment than to be damned; that there remains ſome mercy ſtill in the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice which God exerciſes againſt the ſinners in Hell; and that is great favour that they are not conſumed by the Fire that burns them. Non-entity is a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er evil than Hell; and that is it which the Sages preach to the Gnomes, when they call them together to make known to them the wrong they do in prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Death to Immortality, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſs of Nothing to the hope of a Bleſſed Eternity, which they might have a right to poſſeſs, if they would ally themſelves to Men, without exacting from them thoſe Criminal Renunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Some of them believe us, and we marry them to our Daughters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye preach a Goſpel then to the Subter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean people, Sir</hi> (ſaid I.) Why not <hi>(replied he)</hi> we are their Doctors, as well as of the people of the Fire, Air, and Water, and Philoſophical Charity is indifferently diffuſed on all thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, as they are more ſubtile, and more knowing than the ordinary ſort of Men; ſo are they more docile
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151429:61"/> and capable of Inſtruction; and they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten to Divine Truths with a reſpect that raviſhes us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It muſt indeed be rav ſhing</hi> (cried I laughing) <hi>to ſee a Caballiſt in a Pulpit holding forth to theſe Gentlemen.</hi> You ſhall have the pleaſure; my Son, when you will (<hi>ſaid the Count</hi>) and if you pleaſe Ill call them together this Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and preach to them about Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night. <hi>At Midnight</hi> (cried I) <hi>I have been told that that is the hour of</hi> Sabat, <hi>or the Devils Night Rendezvous.</hi> The Count fell a laughing; You put me in mind (<hi>ſaid he</hi>) of the Fopperies that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted by Demonographers concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their imaginary <hi>Sabbat.</hi> I wiſh alſo for the rarity of the thing, that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved them likewiſe. <hi>Ha! as to the Tales of the</hi> Sabbat (replied I) <hi>I do aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you I believe not one word of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You do well, my Son (<hi>ſaid he</hi>) for once more, the Devil hath no power ſo to play upon Mankind, nor to converſe with men; far leſs to make himſelf be adored by them, as the Inquiſitors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. The occaſion of this popular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, is, becauſe the Sages, as I have
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151429:61"/> juſt now told you, aſſemble the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Elements, to preach to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem their Myſteries and Morality; and ſeeing it happens commonly that ſome Gnome is cured of his groſs Error, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the horror of Non-entity, and conſents to be immortalized; we give him a Maid, marry him, and celebrate the Wedding with all the rejoycing that the Conqueſt we have made does re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: Theſe are the Dances and Shouts of Joy, which <hi>Ariſtottle</hi> ſays were heard in ſome Iſlands where no Body was ſeen however. The great <hi>Orpheus</hi> was the firſt that called together the Subterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean People, at his firſt meeting <hi>Sebaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> the ancienteſt of the Gnomes, was immortalized; and from that <hi>Sebaſius</hi> the Aſſembly had its name, in which the Sages directed their Speech to him ſo long as he lived; as appears in the Hymns of the Divine <hi>Orpheus.</hi> The ignorant have confounded things, and have taken oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thereupon to tell a thouſand im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies, and to decrie an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly which we only ſummon for the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Supream Being. <hi>I could never have imagined</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>that the night</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151429:62"/> 
                  <hi>was an Aſſembly of Devotion.</hi> It is though, a moſt holy and Cabaliſtick one <hi>(replied he)</hi> which the World will not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be perſwaded of: But ſuch is the deplorable ignorance of this unjuſt Age, men are infatuated with a popular opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and will not be undeceived. It is in vain for the Sages to ſpeak, Fools are better believed. It is in vain for a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher evidently to demonſtrate the Falſity of the Notions that Men have framed to themſelves, and give evident proofs to the contrary; let him uſe what Experiment and ſolid Reaſon he can: If a man in a Hood appear, who will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to falſifie it; Experience and Demonſtration are baffled, and Truth cannot again recover its right. Men believe this Hood more than their own Eyes. There hath been a memorable inſtance of this Popular Infatuation in your own <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Famous Cabaliſt <hi>Zedechias</hi> had a mind, in the Reign of your King <hi>Pepin,</hi> to convince the World that the Elements were inhabited by all thoſe People, whoſe Nature I have already deſcribed to you. The Expedient he conceited,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151429:62"/> was to adviſe the Sylphs to ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves publickly in the Air; they did it with great Pomp and Magnificence. Theſe admirable Creatures were ſeen in the Air in Humane Shape, ſometimes in Battel Array, marching in good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſtanding to their Arms, or encam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped under rich Pavillions: ſometimes in a Fleet of Aereal Ships of an admirable Build, which ſailed with gentle <hi>Zephirs.</hi> What became of it? Do you think that the ignorant Age fell to reaſon on the Nature of thoſe marvellous Spectacles? No ſuch matter. The People believed at firſt that they were Sorcerers, who had got into the Air, to raiſe Tempeſts there, and to ſhowre down Hail upon their Crops. The Learned Divines and Lawyers were quickly of the Opinion of the People, the Emperour believed it alſo; and that ridiculous Notion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed ſo far, that the Wiſe <hi>Charlemaigne,</hi> and after him <hi>Lewis</hi> the Debonaire, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed heavy puniſhments upon all thoſe pretended Tyrants of the Air. This you may ſee in the Firſt Chapter of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitular Decrees of thoſe two Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:151429:63"/>
               <p>The Sylphs perceiving that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Pedants, and the Crowned Heads themſelves, conſpired thus againſt them, reſolved that they might make them loſe the bad Opinion which they had of their innocent Fleet, to carry away men from all parts, to ſhew them their Fair Women, their Republick, &amp; Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then to drop them in ſeveral places of the World. They did as they projected, the People ſeeing Men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend, came running from all parts, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed with an Opinion that they were Sorcerers, who detached themſelves from their Companions, that they might poiſon the Fruits and the Waters; and according to the rage that is inſpired by ſuch imaginations, they dragged the poor innocent men to puniſhment. It is incredible what a vaſt number of them periſhed by Fire and Water in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>One day amongſt the reſt it happened at <hi>Lyons,</hi> that three Men and a Woman deſcended in thoſe Aereal Ships; the whole City gather about them, cry they are Magicians, and that <hi>Grimoald</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Benevent,</hi> the Enemy of <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maigne,</hi>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:151429:63"/> ſent them to deſtroy the Crops of <hi>France.</hi> It was to no purpoſe for the four Innocents to ſay for their juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that they were of the ſame Countrey; that they were lately carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed way by miraculous men, who ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them unheard of Wonders, and prayed them to relate them. The infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated People, will not hear their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; but was going to throw them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Fire, when the good man <hi>Ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lyons,</hi> who whil'ſt he was a Monk, had obtained great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in that City, came running upon the News; and having heard the Peoples Accuſation, and the Defence of the Accuſed, gravely pronounced that both were falſe. That it was not true that theſe Men came down out of the Air, and that what they affirmed to have ſeen there, was abſolutely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</p>
               <p>The People believed what good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Agobard</hi> ſaid, better than their own Eyes; was pacified, ſet at liberty the four Ambaſſadors of the Sylphs, and received with admiration the Book which <hi>Agobard</hi> wrote to confirm the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151429:64"/> Sentence he had pronounced. Thus was the Teſtimony of theſe four Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made frivolous.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, ſeeing they eſcaped puniſhment, they were free to relate what they had ſeen; which was not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together fruitleſs: for if you remember the Age of <hi>Charlemaigne</hi> abounded in Heroick Men. And this is a ſign that the Woman who had been with the Sylphs, obtained Credit amongſt the Ladies of thoſe Times; and that by the grace of God many Sylphs were immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, many Sylphides became likewiſe Immortal, by the relation that theſe three Men gave of their Beauty; which obliged the people of that Age to apply themſelves a little to Philoſophy; and from thence have come all the Stories of Fairies which you find in the amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Legends of the Age of <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maigne,</hi> and the ſucceeding. And theſe pretended Fairies were nothing elſe but Sylphides and Nymphs. Have you read the Stories of thoſe Heroes and Fairies? <hi>No, Sir</hi> (ſaid I.)</p>
               <p>I am ſorry for that (<hi>replied he</hi>) for they would have given you ſome Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151429:64"/> of the State to which the Sages are reſolved one day to reduce the World. Thoſe Heroick Men, thoſe Loves of Nymphs, thoſe Journeys to the Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Paradice, thoſe Palaces and Inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Groves, and all thoſe Charming Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, are but a weak Emblem of the Life that the Sages leads, and what the World ſhall be, when Wiſdom by their means ſhall reign therein<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> There ſhall be none but Heroes in it; the leaſt of our Children ſhall have the might of <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>roaſter, Apollonius,</hi> or <hi>Melchſedec;</hi> and moſt part of them ſhall be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed as the Children that <hi>Adam</hi> would have begotten on <hi>Eve,</hi> had he not ſinned with her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Did you not tell me, Sir</hi> (ſaid I inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting him) <hi>that it was not the will of God that</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve <hi>ſhould have had Children; and that</hi> Eve <hi>ſhould have given her ſelf only to Sylphs or Salamanders?</hi> It is true (ſaid the Count) they ſhould not have procreated the way they did. <hi>Your Cabal Sir</hi> (continued I) <hi>furniſhes Man and Woman then with an Invention of Begetting Children after another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner than the common Method.</hi> Aſſuredly
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151429:65"/> replied he.) <hi>Good now, pray teach me that, Sir</hi> (anſwered I.) You ſhall not know it too day, if you pleaſe (ſaid he laughing) I'll revenge the Quarrel of the people of the Elements, becauſe you have made ſo much difficulty to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive your ſelf of their pretended De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilry. I make no queſtion but your pannick fears are now over. I leave you therefore, that you may have time to meditate and deliberate in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God, to which kind of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Subſtances it will be moſt for his glory and your honour, that you beſtow a ſhare of your Immortality.</p>
               <p>In the mean time I'll go recollect my ſelf a little, for the Diſcourſe that you have put me upon making this night, to the Gnomes. <hi>Go</hi> (ſaid I) <hi>explain to them ſome Chapter of</hi> Averroes? I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve (<hi>ſaid the Count</hi>) I may very well have a little touch at that; for I have <hi>a</hi> Deſign to preach to them the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Man, that I may work upon them to court our Alliance. And after <hi>Ariſtotle Averroes</hi> holds two things which it is fit I ſhould illuſtrate; the one concerning the Nature of the Mind, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151429:65"/> the other about the Chief Good: He ſays, <hi>That there is but one created Mind, which is the Image of the uncreated; and that that Mind alone is ſufficient for all Men.</hi> And as to the Chief Good, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verroes</hi> ſays, <hi>It conſiſts in the Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Angels;</hi> which is not Cabali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick enough: For Man even in this life is created for the Enjoyment of God, as you ſhall one day know, and find by Experience, when you are liſted among the Sages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus ended the</hi> Conference <hi>of the Count of</hi> Gabalis. <hi>He return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed next day, and brought me the Diſcourſe that he made to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean People: It is a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Piece. I would publiſh it, with a Continuation of the</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences <hi>that a Vice-Counteſs and I had with that Great Man, were I ſure that all my Readers had right thoughts, and would not take it amiſs that I make my ſelf merry with Fools. If I perceive
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151429:66"/> that my Book is permitted to do the good that it may produce, and that I be not unjuſtly ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to commend</hi> Secret Sciences, <hi>under pretext of making them ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous; I ſhall continue to pleaſe my ſelf with my Count; and may ſuddenly publiſh another Tome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:151429:66"/>
            <head>A LETTER To my LORD of ****</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> have alwayes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to me ſo affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate to your Friends, that I hope you will pardon the liberty I take in favours of the beſt of mine, to beſeech your Lordship to have the goodneſs for him as to read his Book. I pretend not thereby to engage you in any of the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that my Friend the <hi>Author</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:151429:67"/> may perhaps promiſe to himſelf from that; for <hi>Authors</hi> are apt to conceive great hopes. I have even told him that you make it your honour never to ſpeak, but what you think; and that he is not to expect that you will lay aſide ſo rare a <hi>Quality,</hi> and ſo new at <hi>Court,</hi> to ſay that his Book is good, if you find it bad; but it is my humble deſire only to your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> that you would have the goodneſs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide a <hi>Controverſie</hi> that we have had together. You need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not have ſtudied ſo much <hi>my Lord,</hi> as to become a Prodigy of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> if you thought it not fit to expoſe your ſelf to
<pb facs="tcp:151429:67"/> be conſulted preferably to <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors.</hi> This is then the <hi>Diſpute</hi> that I have with my <hi>Friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would have obliged him wholly to change the Form of his <hi>Work,</hi> the pleaſant ſtrain be handles it in, ſeems not at all proper for the <hi>Subject.</hi> The <hi>Cabal</hi> (I told him) is a ſerious <hi>Science,</hi> which many of my <hi>Friends</hi> ſtudy ſeriouſly; it ought therefore to be refuted the ſame way. Seeing all its <hi>Errors</hi> are about <hi>Divinity,</hi> and that is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry difficult to make a ſerious Man laugh upon any <hi>Subject;</hi> it is moſt dangerous to droll in this, and it is much to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>Devotion</hi> may ſeem in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted
<pb facs="tcp:151429:68"/> therein. A <hi>Cabaliſt</hi> muſt be made to ſpeak like a <hi>Saint,</hi> elſe he acts his <hi>Part</hi> very ill; and if he ſpeak like a <hi>Saint,</hi> by that apparent <hi>Sanctity</hi> he impoſes upon weak Minds, and better perſwades his <hi>Viſions</hi> than all the <hi>Drollery</hi> that may be made on them, can refute them. To this my <hi>Friend</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Preſumption</hi> that <hi>Authors</hi> have when they defend their <hi>Books;</hi> that if the <hi>Cabal</hi> be a ſerious <hi>Science,</hi> then none but Melancholick people apply themſelves to it; and that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at firſt tried the Dogmatick Stile on that <hi>Subject,</hi> he found himſelf ſo ridiculous in treating
<pb facs="tcp:151429:68"/> Fopperies ſeriouſly, that he judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it more proper to turn the <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule</hi> upon the Count <hi>Gabalis.</hi> The <hi>Cabal</hi> (ſaid he) is one of thoſe Chimaera's, which Men authoriſe, when they oppugn them gravely; and which should only be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by Drolling. He is not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of the Fathers, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cited to me <hi>Tertullian.</hi> You who know it better than he and I both, my Lord; judge if the Citation be falſe: <hi>Multa ſunt riſu digna revinci, ne gravitate adorentur.</hi> He ſays that <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> uſes that pretty Sentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Valentinians,</hi> who were a kind of moſt <hi>Enthuſiaſtick Cabaliſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151429:69"/>
            <p>As to Devotion which comes always in play thorowout this <hi>Work</hi> (he ſays) that a <hi>Cabaliſt</hi> muſt unavoidably ſpeak of God: but it is happy, that in this <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> it is of a more unavoidable neceſſity, for preſerving the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baliſtick Character,</hi> never to ſpeak of God, but with extream <hi>Veneration;</hi> ſo <hi>Religion</hi> can receive no blemish: and the weak Wits muſt be ſillier than the Lord <hi>Gabalis,</hi> if they ſuffer themſelves to be inchanted by that Extravagant <hi>Devotion;</hi> or if the <hi>Raillery</hi> that is put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, remove not the <hi>Charm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe and many other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which I shall not alledge
<pb facs="tcp:151429:69"/> here, becauſe I have a Mind your Lordship should be of my Opinion; my Friend pretends that he ought to write againſt the <hi>Cabal</hi> merrily. Reconcile us if you pleaſe, I hold it beſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt the <hi>Cabaliſts</hi> and all the <hi>Secret Sciences,</hi> by ſerious and vigorous Arguments. He ſaith that <hi>Truth</hi> is naturally brisk, and that it is far more powerful when it laughs: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe an ancient <hi>Author,</hi> whom without doubt, you know, ſays in a place, which, conſidering the excellent Memory God hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed you with, you will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remember; <hi>Convenit Verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ridere, quia laetans.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151429:70"/>
            <p>He adds, That the <hi>Secret Sciences</hi> are dangerous, if they be not handled in a ſtrain that may make them contemptible; expoſing their ridiculous <hi>Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and taking off People from lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing time in the Study of them; by shewing them the depth, and diſcovering the extravagancy thereof. Give Sentence, <hi>my Lord,</hi> theſe are our Reaſons. I shall receive your Verdict with the reſpect which you know does always accompany the Zeal wherewith I am</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble and obedient Servant,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:151429:70"/>
            <head>A CATALOGUE <hi>Of ſome</hi> BOOKS <hi>ſold by</hi> ROBERT HARFORD <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in</hi> Cornhil <hi>near the</hi> Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>GELL's Remains,</hi> being ſundry Pious and Learned Notes and Obſervations on the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament;</hi> Opening and Explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it: wherein Jeſus Chriſt, as yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, too day, and the ſame for ever; is illuſtrated: by that learned and judicious Man Dr. <hi>R. Gell,</hi> late Rector of St. <hi>Mary Aldermanbury, London;</hi> in two Volumes <hi>Folio.</hi> Price 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian Religions Appeal from the groundleſs prejudice of the Scepticks, to the Bar of Common Reaſon;</hi> wherein is proved, 1. That that the Apoſtles did not delude
<pb facs="tcp:151429:71"/> the World. 2. Nor were themſelves deluded. 3. Scripture Matters of Faith have the beſt Evidence. 4. The Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Scriptures is as demonſtrable as the Being of a Deity. By <hi>John Smith</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>Colcheſter. Folio,</hi> price 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> paraphraſed and turned into Engliſh Verſe, according to the Common Meeter; as they are uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſung in Pariſh Churches. By <hi>Miles Smith Octavo,</hi> price 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Ruin of Papacy,</hi> Or a Clear Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplay of Simony of the Romiſh Clergy; with a Circulatory Letter to the Fathers of thoſe Virgins that deſert their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to turn Nuns: By the Learned Pen of that Famous Divine <hi>Peter du Moulin, Octavo,</hi> price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The Sphere of <hi>Marcus Manilius,</hi> made an Engliſh-Poem, with Learned Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and a large Appendix; reciting the Names of Ancient and Modern A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomers: With ſomething memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of them. Illuſtrated with Copper Cuts. By <hi>Edward Sherburne</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>Folio,</hi> price 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The Admired Piece of Phyſiognomy
<pb facs="tcp:151429:71"/> and Chyromancy, the Symmetrical Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions and Signal Moles of the Body, fully and accurately explained; with their Natural Predictive Significations, both to Men and Women: Being De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighful and Profitable. With the Subject of Dreams made plain. Whereunto is added the Art of Memory. By <hi>Richard Saunders.</hi> Illuſtrated with Cuts and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures. <hi>Folio,</hi> price bound 12 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The Inſtitution of the Laws and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter, adorned with many Sculptures in Copper: By <hi>Elias Aſhmole</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor</hi> Herald at Arms. <hi>Folio,</hi> price bound 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pharamond,</hi> That Fam'd Romance, being an Excellent Hiſtory of <hi>France.</hi> In Twelve Parts. By the Author of <hi>Cleopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra</hi> and <hi>Caſſandra. Folio,</hi> price bound 30 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The New World of Words,</hi> or, A Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al Engliſh Dictionary: Containing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roper Significations and Etimologies of all Words derived from other Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Together with the Definitions of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe Terms that conduce to the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tanding of any of the Arts and Sciences. The Fourth Edition, with many Uſeful
<pb facs="tcp:151429:72"/> Additions. Collected and Publiſhed by <hi>E. P. Folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Longitude not found,</hi> or, An Anſwer to a Treatiſe written by <hi>Henry Bond</hi> Senior, ſhewing a way to find the Longitude by the Magnetical Inclinatory Needle: Wherein is proved, That the Longitude is not, nor cannot be found by the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netical Inclinatory Needle, By <hi>Peter Blackborrow</hi> Gent. price 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Catalogus Stellarum Auſtralium, ſive Supplementum Catalogi Tichonici; exhibens Longitudines &amp; Latitudines Stellarum Fixarum: Quae, prope Polum Antarcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum ſitae, in Horizonte <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>raniburgico Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choni in conſpicuae fuere, accurato Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo ex Diſtantiis ſupputatas, &amp; ad Annum</hi> 1677, <hi>&amp;c. Authore</hi> Edmundo Halleio, <hi>e Colleg.</hi> Reg. Oxon. <hi>Quarto,</hi> price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Jeſuits Catechiſme</hi> according to Saint <hi>Ignatius Loyola Quarto,</hi> price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>A Treatiſe of Taxes and Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Very requiſite for Stateſmen. <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi> price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The Priviledges and Practices of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments in <hi>England</hi> Collected out of the Common Laws of this Land. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to the High Court of Parliament. <hi>Quarto,</hi> price 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151429:72"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Accompliſhed Cook,</hi> or, The My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the whole Art of Cookery. By <hi>Robert May</hi> in <hi>Octavo,</hi> price bound 5 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Mathematical Compendium,</hi> or, Uſeful Practices in Arithmetick, Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry, Aſtronomy, and Navigation; Embattelling and Quartering of Armies, Fortification and Gunnery; Gauging and Dialling: Explaining the Logarithms. With new Indices, <hi>Nepair</hi>'s Rods or Bones: Making of Movements, and Application of <hi>Pendulums.</hi> With the Projection of the Sphere for an Univerſal Dial, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Collected out of the Notes and Papers of Sir <hi>Jonas Moore.</hi> By <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Stephenſon.</hi> The Second Edition, with many Additions. In Twelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Art of Wart,</hi> and the way that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s at preſent practiſed in <hi>France.</hi> In two Parts. <hi>Octavo,</hi> price bound 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Treatiſe of Arms and Engines of War,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nriched with 20 Copper Plates; out of <hi>French,</hi> in <hi>Octavo,</hi> price bound 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d,</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The Military Duties of the Officers of Horſe, containing the Exerciſes of the Cavalry, according to the preſent Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tice of the Times. Illuſtrated with Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Plates; <hi>Octavo</hi> price 2 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151429:73"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Humane Prudence,</hi> or the ſeveral ways for a man to advance himſelf at Court. In Twelves, price bound 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Indiculus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis,</hi> Or the Univerſe in Epitome: Wherein the Names of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the Works of Nature, of all Arts and Sciences, with their moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Terms, are in Engliſh, Latine, and French, Methodically and diſtinctly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Compoſed at firſt in French and Latine, for the uſe of the Dauphin of <hi>France;</hi> by the Learned <hi>T. Pomey</hi> Ahd now made Engliſh, by <hi>A. Lovell M. A.</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151429:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
